<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The temple re-built. A discourse on Zachary 6.13. Preached at a generall meeting of the associated ministers of the county of Cumberland at Keswick, May 19. By Richard Gilpin, pastor of the church at Graistock in Cumberland.</title>
            <author>Gilpin, Richard, 1625-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G778</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201007</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825114</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825114</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29487</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42782)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29487)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1760:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The temple re-built. A discourse on Zachary 6.13. Preached at a generall meeting of the associated ministers of the county of Cumberland at Keswick, May 19. By Richard Gilpin, pastor of the church at Graistock in Cumberland.</title>
                  <author>Gilpin, Richard, 1625-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by E.T. for Luke Fawne, at the Parrat in Pauls-Church-yard, and are to be sold by Richard Scott, Bookseller in Carlisle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Zechariah VI, 13 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29487:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TEMPLE RE-BUILT. A DISCOURSE On Zachary 6.13. Preached at a GENERALL MEETING of the ASSOCIATED MINISTERS Of the <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Cumberland</hi> at <hi>Keſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, May</hi> 19. By <hi>RICHARD GILPIN,</hi> Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Grai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock</hi> in <hi>Cumberland.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Not by Might, nor by Power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Zach. 4. v. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. T.</hi> for <hi>Luke Fawne,</hi> at the Parrat in Pauls-Church-yard, and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Scott,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Carliſle.</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:29487:2"/>
            <p>WEe the Aſſociate Miniſters of the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> do earneſtly deſire our Reverend Brother, Mr. <hi>Richard Gilpin,</hi> to Print his Acceptable Sermon, Preached this day at our Generall Meeting,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Keſwick</hi> in <hi>Cumberland.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 20. 1658.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed by <hi>TIMOTHY T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LLIE Moderator</hi> Pro Temp. <hi>IOHN IACKSON, Scribe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29487:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To my Reverend, Peaceable and dearly Beloved Brethren,</hi> THE ASSOCIATED MINISTERS of the County of CUMBERLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHat your <hi>Commands</hi> have <hi>wreſted</hi> from me (for of that force and preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency with me are your deſires) <hi>I</hi> new lay it at your <hi>feet.</hi> If I could have prevailed with you to have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered your <hi>vote,</hi> or (after you had paſſed it) durſt have <hi>reſiſted;</hi> this had gone no further then your own <hi>hearing.</hi> But when you would not be <hi>perſwaded,</hi> I endeavoured to conform my ſelf to thoſe Chriſtians in <hi>Act. 21.14.</hi> and took up with that which put a ſtop to their intreaties, <hi>The will of the Lord be done,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:29487:3"/>remembring that ſpeech of <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi> to his Councel, <hi>Aequius eſt, ut ego tot talium amicorum conſilium ſequar, quam, ut tot tales amici meam unius ſequantur volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well! you have ſaved me the labour of an <hi>Apology,</hi> and, having <hi>adopted</hi> this iſſue for your own, you muſt expect not onely to bear a ſhare <hi>with me</hi> in the <hi>cenſures</hi> which may be occaſioned by its <hi>deformity;</hi> but muſt <hi>wholly</hi> by your ſelves bear <hi>all</hi> the blame of <hi>troubling</hi> the world with it: and if it ſhould be raiſed (above its own deſerts) to be of any uſe in the Church by the hand of him who <hi>worketh mightily</hi> (ſometimes) by <hi>unlikely means</hi> (though I cannot diſcover within <hi>kenning</hi> any ground for ſuch an expectation, but this, That it was the <hi>reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, ſolemn intreaty</hi> and <hi>order</hi> of <hi>ſuch,</hi> and ſo <hi>ſerious</hi> a company:) yet, if it ſhould be thus bleſſed, I am willing (for my part) that, next to God, the thanks be wholly yours.</p>
            <p>Among the many favours which God hath beſtowed upon us, and the <hi>County</hi> where we live; this is none of the leaſt, That God hath <hi>poured</hi> upon us ſome meaſure of his Spirit of <hi>peace,</hi> and hath <hi>bleſſed</hi> us thus far in it; the bleſſed <hi>fruits</hi> of concord which we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready taſted (if we ſhould never ſee more) together with the <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> of the teſtimony of Conſcience (thus far acquitting us from the guilt of <hi>Church-murther</hi>) are a ſufficient <hi>recompence</hi> for all the <hi>trouble</hi> it hath given us. Great are the <hi>advantages</hi> that we and our people have from hence; <hi>united</hi> Counſels promiſe more <hi>ſafety,</hi> and juſtly challenge a greater <hi>reſpect</hi> and <hi>reverence</hi> to our proceedings: our <hi>joint concurrence</hi> in what we pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice puts us in a better <hi>poſture</hi> of mutual <hi>communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of gifts, graces, ſtrength and aſſiſtance (ſtones in <hi>conjunction</hi> as in an arch, will ſupport one another and
<pb facs="tcp:29487:3"/>bear up the weight of the whole Fabrick, which, being <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> and <hi>ſcattered,</hi> they cannot do) beſides, it may do much to cure that <hi>itch</hi> after <hi>novelties,</hi> that <hi>intemperancy</hi> of roaving, <hi>doubting</hi> and <hi>ſcepticiſm</hi> in Chriſtians about Government, when they ſee their leaders <hi>unanimous,</hi> and not ſo <hi>wedded</hi> to their opinions as to undo the Church for <hi>Punctilios;</hi> and that which is more, while others are toiling in the <hi>ſweat</hi> &amp; <hi>duſt</hi> of diſputations, and as <hi>fruitleſly</hi> wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves as the <hi>Grammarians</hi> in <hi>Eraſmus</hi> about find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the meaning of <hi>Anticomarita;</hi> we have happily gained an opportunity of <hi>preſſing</hi> and <hi>practiſing</hi> the <hi>great</hi> things of Gods Law. <hi>Diſputings</hi> often drown the <hi>voice</hi> of truth by their noiſe and clamour, they <hi>prodigally la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh</hi> out the ſpirits and affections of men on <hi>ſmaller</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which ſhould be reſerved for <hi>higher</hi> objects; and, though they have their <hi>fruits,</hi> yet are they like trees growing upon a <hi>rocky precipice,</hi> where the fruit cannot be gathered by all, and not by any without difficulty and hazard.</p>
            <p>Brethren, Tou have put your hands to this work,<note place="margin">2 John 8.</note> 
               <hi>Now look to your ſelves, that you looſe not thoſe things which ye have wrought, but that ye receive a full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi> do not think (now that the work is upon the <hi>wheels</hi>) that you may <hi>ſlacken</hi> your <hi>diligence,</hi> or <hi>abate</hi> any thing of your <hi>watchfulneſs</hi> againſt temptations, or of the <hi>jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies</hi> and <hi>ſuſpicions</hi> over your own hearts. There is yet much to do, and if there were not;<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteret jam metae vicinum curſum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere? An magis intendere?</note> yet (as <hi>Diogenes</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the man that perſwaded him to give over ſtudy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was grown old) the nearer you come to the <hi>mark</hi> you ſhould put forth <hi>more</hi> ſtrength, &amp; <hi>run</hi> the <hi>faſter.</hi> Dream not of eaſe in an imployment of this nature, God, Angels and <hi>men</hi> have their eyes upon you to ſee how you will <hi>beſtir</hi> your ſelves; it is your <hi>duty</hi> and not a matter of unneceſſary <hi>courteſy,</hi> which you may give or hold back at your pleaſure:<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.15.</note> he that hath commanded you <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to give your ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:29487:4"/>up wholly to theſe things; will not take himſelf to be <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden</hi> to you when you have done your <hi>beſt:</hi> neither is it any <hi>diſparagement</hi> to you to become even <hi>ſervants</hi> to any; ſo that you may but <hi>gain</hi> them, and <hi>forward</hi> Chriſts work; they that think it below them to trouble themſelves ſo much with <hi>Catechizing, reproof, admonition,</hi> &amp;c. are of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemaeus</hi> his mind, who changed the title of <hi>Heraclides</hi> his book from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; as if laboriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs were nothing but an <hi>Aſs-like</hi> dulneſs, making a man <hi>crouch</hi> under every <hi>burthen;</hi> but God having made the <hi>ox</hi> which treads out the corn to be the <hi>Hieroglyphick</hi> of your imployment; he doth thereby teach you that <hi>labour</hi> and <hi>patience</hi> are ſo far from being a <hi>diſgrace</hi> to you, that they are <hi>neceſſary</hi> qualifications for the calling of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> (I ſuppoſe) you all <hi>expect,</hi> and partly <hi>find</hi> already, can any man think otherwiſe but that they who are like <hi>bullocks, unaccuſtomed</hi> to the <hi>yoke</hi> will <hi>ſtruggle?</hi> is it a wonder if they think all <hi>bonds</hi> to be <hi>fetters?</hi> every <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint</hi> to be <hi>cruelty,</hi> and the <hi>dreſſing</hi> of their wounds (though in order to their cure and Salvation) to be <hi>unſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable tyranny?</hi> but what then! is the worke ever the worſe for that? hath not God called you out to <hi>oppoſe</hi> the Carnall <hi>intereſts</hi> and <hi>deſires</hi> of men? the <hi>Critick</hi> before mentioned (when he thruſt into the theatre againſt the throng of people coming out; (being asked the reaſon, gives this account of it, <hi>hoc in omni vita facere ſtudio:</hi> He thought it was the <hi>perfection</hi> of Phyloſophy to go <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Generality</hi> of men, and the <hi>likelieſt</hi> way to find out <hi>Vertue;</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> ſhewing himſelfe courteous to all, was thus cenſured, <hi>quid illi tribuendum eſt, qui tot annos in philoſophia verſatus, nullum hactenus dolore affecit;</hi> you know how to apply it, what a ſhame would it be that we who have <hi>better inſtructions, greater obligations,</hi> and <hi>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:29487:4"/>promiſes</hi> of helpe ſhould give off with the excuſe of the <hi>ſluggard?</hi> Oh <hi>there is a Lion in the way!</hi> let us not fear, difficulties there will be, but they are <hi>onely</hi> or <hi>moſtly</hi> diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties to the <hi>fearfull</hi> and <hi>unbelieving,</hi> which do their work negligently and by halves; be couragious and faithfull, and God will make the <hi>rough</hi> wayes <hi>plain</hi> before you.</p>
            <p>As for the deſign of <hi>peace</hi> it ſelfe, though it may be <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly</hi> maligned and whiſpered againſt, yet I do not expect to ſee any ſo <hi>hardy</hi> as to take up <hi>Armes</hi> againſt it <hi>publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> it hath ſuch a <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>majeſty</hi> in it as will keep off ſuch <hi>attempts;</hi> except peradventure ſome mans <hi>ignorant zeale</hi> or <hi>vain-glory</hi> put him upon, ſeeking a <hi>name,</hi> (as he did who burnt <hi>Diana's</hi> Temple) by <hi>blemiſhing</hi> ſomething of more then ordinary worth. I perceive by Mr. <hi>Firmius</hi> late book of Sciſme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that ſome upon their own <hi>miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> have <hi>privately</hi> excepted againſt the firſt rule in our book of aſſociation, p. <hi>3.</hi> Wherein we ſay, <hi>That in the exerciſe of Diſcipline it is not only the moſt ſafe courſe, but alſo moſt conducing to brotherly union and ſatisfaction, that particular Churches carry on as much of their work with joynt and mutuall aſſiſtance, as they can with conveniency and edification, and as little as may be in their actings, to ſtand diſtinctly by themſelves, and apart from each other:</hi> he indeed hath anſwered for us (and for the kindneſſe, I ſhall take the boldneſſe to return him thanks in your names,) and hath <hi>hit</hi> our <hi>ſence</hi> right enough; the truth is, the thing is ſo <hi>plain,</hi> that I wonder any body (let his prejudice be as ſtrong as it may be) ſhould <hi>miſſe</hi> it: he might have ſeen that we intend not to <hi>cut off the liberty of particular Congregations by the middle,</hi> by that Principle. <hi>1.</hi> The words <hi>conveniency</hi> and <hi>edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> would have told them as much; they ſtand not there for <hi>Cyphers. 2.</hi> The <hi>whole book</hi> (if he had diligently conſidered it,) would have taken that <hi>exception off;</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:29487:5"/>what we <hi>build</hi> upon that <hi>bottom</hi> is there <hi>expreſſed:</hi> now, what <hi>article</hi> or <hi>line</hi> can be find which may bear that charge? <hi>3.</hi> Our <hi>Practiſe</hi> ſpeaks for us, let him or others <hi>enquire,</hi> and then <hi>accuſe</hi> if they have cauſe; but <hi>I</hi> ſee men <hi>ſpeak</hi> in their <hi>haſt:</hi> tis now ſo common for men to <hi>write</hi> againſt books before they <hi>underſtand</hi> them; that this fault may well be pardoned by the <hi>courteſy of England.</hi> Pardon this prolixity and plainneſs, and go on yet to be more <hi>diligent</hi> and <hi>peaceful. Warn the unruly, ſupport the weak, be patient towards all men; be enſamples to the flock. And, when the chief Sepherd ſhall appear, you ſhall receive a Crown of Glory that fadeth not away.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Graiſtock, <date>Aug. <hi>1. 1658.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your unworthy fellow-ſervant RICHARD GILPIN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29487:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ZACH. 6 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Even he ſhall build the Temple of the Lord, and he ſhall bear the glory, and ſhall ſit and rule upon his throne, and he ſhall be a Prieſt upon his Throne, and the Counſell of peace ſhall be between them both.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have read to you a very glorious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe concerning the reparation of Gods Temple, and (me thinks) it contains a <hi>Cordiall</hi> abundantly ſufficient to <hi>quell</hi> thoſe <hi>feares</hi> about the ſtate of the Church: wherewith the mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Sion have <hi>obſtructed</hi> their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and <hi>diſtreſſed</hi> their hearts.</p>
            <p>This Prophet is full of Propheticall viſions: God raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him up with <hi>Haggai,</hi> (who began to Propheſie but two moneths before him, as appeares by the date of their Propheſies) for the ſtrengthning of the hands of the people in building the houſe of the Lord. Their diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements were many; <hi>Darius</hi> his Decree and Commiſſion for the work was not yet come forth, as appeares from <hi>Ezra, Chap.</hi> 5, and 6. <hi>Cyrus</hi> indeed had given Commandment before to build the houſe of the Lord, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 1.2. But, upon the miſinformation of the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29487:6"/>of <hi>Judah,</hi> who had <hi>hired Counſellors againſt them to fruſtrate their purpoſe, the work</hi> ceaſeth; Ezra 4.24. and that for a long time; tis the pleaſure of <hi>Artaxerxes Ahaſuerus,</hi> (for ſome ſuppoſe that theſe two names de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign but one perſon, <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> being a common name to the Kings of <hi>Perſia</hi>) he hath weighty reaſons of <hi>ſtate</hi> for it, he feares (and his Counſellors ſuggeſt) that, if the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> flouriſh, it may <hi>indammage</hi> the King; by <hi>incroaching</hi> upon his rights, by <hi>occaſioning tumults</hi> and diviſions, or, by <hi>hightning</hi> the ſpirits of his Subjects to <hi>inſoleney</hi> and <hi>ſtubbornneſſe.</hi> Theſe have been ſtill the ſecret <hi>jealouſies,</hi> and open <hi>outcries</hi> too, ſome times, of <hi>States-men</hi> and others, againſt <hi>reformation</hi> and the Government of the Church; this hath commonly made them fearfull of entruſting the Church with any <hi>Power,</hi> which they themſelves might not <hi>hold</hi> the <hi>reins</hi> of: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances hereof are frequent in hiſtory.</p>
            <p>Beſides this hinderance from their <hi>enemies,</hi> their own <hi>brethren</hi> weaken their hands; ſome are back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and think they muſt <hi>wait</hi> till <hi>another</hi> time; they ſay the <hi>time is not come, the time that the Lords houſe ſhould be built;</hi> Hag. 1, 2. Others <hi>weep</hi> at the <hi>laying</hi> of the <hi>foundation,</hi> and think it <hi>contemptible</hi> in compariſon of the <hi>former</hi> building that was deſtroyed; <hi>Ezr.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.3. Thus (as is uſuall in all refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations) they oppoſe their <hi>own happineſs;</hi> ſome from a timerous, daſtardly <hi>ſloathfulneſs;</hi> others, from <hi>prejudice, emulation,</hi> and <hi>croſſeneſſe</hi> of nature.</p>
            <p>Yet, that Gods intended work might not fall to the ground, he is pleaſed to provide extraordinary <hi>encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements</hi> for them, by theſe two Propets, <hi>Haggai,</hi> and <hi>Zachary:</hi> where (amongſt other things) the people are aſſured from God of his <hi>preſence</hi> with them; of the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of their enemies; of the certain <hi>proſpering</hi> and <hi>finiſhing</hi> of their work; of his ſpecial <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> in, and <hi>acceptance</hi> of, their ſervices: he foretells them the <hi>birth, offices,</hi> and <hi>ſufferings</hi> of Chriſt; the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>Jewes</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29487:6"/>by the <hi>Romans;</hi> their calling again and repentance; and, generally, from the <hi>Temple</hi> which they were building, and the glory of it; he takes occaſion to Propheſie of the <hi>beauty</hi> of that <hi>ſpirituall</hi> houſe, the Church of God, in the times of the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>This Text which I am now upon, by the general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Interpreters, relates to the time after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt in the fleſh: the Analyſis of the context is plain and obvious, wherein the Prophet preſents:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Type, that was <hi>Joſhua</hi> the High Prieſt crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. He was a great inſtrument in this work; God reſolves to put a glory upon the inſtruments of his ſervice: he will put his own <hi>Crown</hi> upon their <hi>head,</hi> and cloath them with his own <hi>garments</hi> of <hi>praiſe,</hi> and make their very adverſaries to proclaim before them, <hi>Lo, thus ſhal it be done to the man whom the King wil honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The thing typified, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. which is the <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>dignity</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, in <hi>building</hi> and <hi>governing</hi> the New-Teſtament-Church; though God in the type intended a ſpeciall reſpect to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> for his forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and zeale in repairing the Temple; yet, he immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately calls off their thoughts from <hi>Joſhua,</hi> to fix them upon the Man whoſe name is the <hi>Branch;</hi> that they might contemplate the greater work of him that was to come, and his greater praiſe.</p>
            <p>That by that phraſe <hi>[The Man whoſe Name is the Branch]</hi> both in this place, and alſo <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.8. Chriſt is to be underſtood, is evident enough; I might fetch a proofe of it from the <hi>Criticks;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tſemach,</hi> which is the word here uſed for <hi>Branch,</hi> is <hi>Synonimus,</hi> of the ſame ſignification with <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Netzer,</hi> (for they are promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly rendred by the LXX, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.) Now (as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> obſerves) <hi>Netzer</hi> is but twice found among the Prophets <hi>(haebraicè, ſcilicet, loquentes, non Caldaiſantes,)</hi> and, in both places referred to Chriſt: ſo, theſe two names ſeeme to be peculiarly appropriated to him: that <hi>Rod</hi> out of <hi>the ſtem of Jeſs, and the branch out of his root,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:29487:7"/>in Eſa. 11.1. Cannot be applyed to any but Chriſt, as the following verſes declare; I might add further ſtrength to this from the uſuall interpretation of <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. <hi>ult. That it might be fulfilled which was ſpoken by the Prophets: He ſhall be called a Nazarene;</hi> This is generally conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that his <hi>dwelling</hi> at <hi>Nazareth</hi> was <hi>providentiall,</hi> that the <hi>place</hi> might give the <hi>riſe,</hi> and occaſion to that <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Nazarene,</hi> which was given to Chriſt long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Old Teſtament upon <hi>another account.</hi> The place (as <hi>Spanhemius</hi> obſerves) is difficult and very <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious</hi> to the <hi>cavills</hi> of the Jewes;<note place="margin">Dub. Evan. par. <hi>2.</hi> Dub. <hi>87.</hi>
               </note> and the <hi>pinch</hi> of the queſtion lies here, <hi>Where is Chriſt called a Nazarene in the Prophets?</hi> tis anſwered (both by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as <hi>Salmero, Maldonate, Janſenius,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as <hi>Tremelius, Pareus, Piſcator, Cauſabon, Junius, Engliſh Annotations,</hi> &amp;c.) That he is ſo called in thoſe places of <hi>Eſay</hi> and <hi>Zachariah,</hi> where he is termed, <hi>Netzer,</hi> and <hi>Tſemach,</hi> a <hi>Branch;</hi> others indeed (as <hi>Bucer, Calvin, Chemnitius, Perkins,</hi> &amp;c.) though they keep to the ſame <hi>ground</hi> of <hi>expoſition</hi> with the former, yet, they <hi>diſſent</hi> from them in <hi>anſwering</hi> the Queſtion, and do rather think that <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. <hi>ult.</hi> refers to thoſe places where Chriſt is either <hi>expreſly</hi> called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>nazir, nazaraens, ſeparatus,</hi> one ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated or ſet apart to God (as in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. where Chriſt is called the <hi>moſt Holy</hi>) or <hi>typified</hi> by thoſe that were called <hi>Nazaraei,</hi> or ſepareted (as <hi>Joſeph, Gen.</hi> 49.26. Who was a Type of Chriſt, and there ſaid to be ſeparated from his brethren, and <hi>Sampſon Judg.</hi> 13.5.) This anſwer avoids many objections wherewith the other interpretation is encumbered; How <hi>Oſiander</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties the knot, or how ſome of the <hi>Papiſts cut</hi> it; I ſhall not trouble you: tis enough to our purpoſe to know, that however they differ about the expoſition of <hi>Matthew,</hi> yet, all <hi>agree</hi> that the terme, <hi>[the Branch]</hi> undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belongs to Chriſt in this place.</p>
            <p>In the Text the Prophet layes open four things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He foretells the great <hi>work</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>he ſhall build the Temple of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:29487:7"/>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>glory</hi> of that <hi>imployment,</hi> and his <hi>intereſt</hi> in it; the building ſhall be magnificent and beautifull, the beholders ſhall with ſhoutings cry <hi>grace, grace unto it,</hi> and whatever the inſtruments are, or have done, Chriſt <hi>ſhall bear away the Glory;</hi> tis a praiſe like that of Eſa. 22.24. where tis ſaid of <hi>Eliakim,</hi> they <hi>ſhall hang upon him all the glory of his fathers houſe;</hi> Chriſt ſhall not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be the great <hi>ſtandard-bearer</hi> to diſplay the Churches <hi>glory,</hi> and the <hi>naile</hi> to <hi>ſupport</hi> and bear the weight of it: but he alſo ſhall have all the <hi>honour aſcribed</hi> to him: his ſervants ſhall ſo <hi>heape</hi> their praiſes upon him, that the glory of the inſtruments ſhall be <hi>eclipſed,</hi> and ſeem <hi>nothing</hi> in compariſon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He explains the <hi>manner</hi> of this <hi>undertaking,</hi> the <hi>way</hi> that Chriſt will take, and the <hi>meanes</hi> he will uſe for the building of his Temple, which ſhall be 1. By redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his people under <hi>government</hi> and rule, by making them <hi>ſtoop</hi> to his <hi>Scepter: He ſhall ſit and rule.</hi> 2. By the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of <hi>Ordinances: He ſhall be a Prieſt.</hi> 3. By the <hi>Exaltation</hi> of both, when they have <hi>power</hi> and <hi>efficacy</hi> in them, when diſcipline and Ordinances are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that others go another way in the Expofition of this place, <hi>underſtanding</hi> by it the <hi>Kingly</hi> and <hi>Prieſtly</hi> Offices of Chriſt: neither do I exclude them from this work of Temple-reparation: for it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denyed but that the Government and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Church do proceed from the Offices of Chriſt; yet cannot I think that this Text intends <hi>one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> a <hi>declaration</hi> of the offices that Chriſt muſt have and execute for the Salvation of ſinners, for 1. The <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick</hi> Office is not mentioned in the Text, and then it would ſeem to be leſſe uſefull, this will have ſome <hi>harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in it, notwithſtanding that <hi>plea</hi> come in to allay it, <hi>That it is included in the other two Offices,</hi> the Text is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry punctuall, <hi>it ſhall be between them both.</hi> 2. This would reſtrain the Text to the dayes wherein Chriſt was in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29487:8"/>fleſh; for, granting it to be underſtood of offices, none will ſay, that the Text ſpeaks of conferring <hi>new</hi> Offices on Chriſt, which he had not, or exerciſed not before; and then muſt they expound it of the more <hi>remarkable execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of thoſe offices, in teaching miracles, and ſuffering, whilſt Chriſt was on earth; and this ſeems not a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient, if the context be well weighed. Now if any will extend it beyond the death of Chriſt, then they come to what I have aſſerted. 3. The Text ſpeaks not of <hi>conſtituting</hi> a Church: but of <hi>reſtauration</hi> and re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment. 4. This bleſſing of Chriſts <hi>building,</hi> &amp;c. is promiſed <hi>conditionally,</hi> v. 15. <hi>It ſhall come to paſs, if ye will diligently obey the voice of the Lord;</hi> and the time of its accompliſhment feems to be ſtated, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> ſhall combine with the <hi>Jewes</hi> in building, <hi>they that are afar off ſhall come and build in the Temple.</hi> v. 15. This place then (as it ſeems to me) doth not well ſuit with that interpretation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Prophet explains what is the glorious accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of that ſtructure, to wit <hi>Peace,</hi> iſſuing from the <hi>throne,</hi> the vigorous adminiſtration of <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Ordinances:</hi> thoſe that do joyntly interpret, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, do here differ; <hi>Junius</hi> thus explains it, He ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the counſell and glad tidings of the Goſpell of peace to both thoſe that are near, and thoſe that are <hi>afar</hi> off; Both to Jewes and Gentiles. <hi>Diodate,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh Annotations,</hi> &amp;c. thus, Theſe two Offices of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and mercy ſhall <hi>agree</hi> and be at <hi>peace</hi> betwixt <hi>themſelves;</hi> thus alſo <hi>Ribera, Summus conſenſus erit inter illos duos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But (ſuppoſing that to be truth, which I laid down before) this is the meaning, The Churches peace (which is the very <hi>end,</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>finiſhing</hi> of Chriſts deſigne) ſhall be brought about and <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> by the power of <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Ordinances, it ſhall proceed from between them both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the avoiding of further trouble, I ſhall gather the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29487:8"/>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Doct.</note> ſumme of the words into this one Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt (when he ariſeth to build his Church) will ſo eſtabliſh the peace thereof, by the power of Government and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that the honour of that glorious work ſhall be chiefly his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I come to the application I ſhall explain theſe four particulars in the Doctrine.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That Chriſt will certainly repair the deſolations of his Church.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That this work, when ever it is done, will be a glorious work.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That whoever be the agents, the honour will be chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſts.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>That this work ſhall then be done, when peace ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the Church, by the power of Government and Ordinances.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Firſt Branch of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> That <hi>Chriſt will certainly repair the deſolations of his Church;</hi> It is a known truth that the Church cannot <hi>totally</hi> fail; though the <hi>buſh</hi> may be in the <hi>fire,</hi> and ſome of the outmoſt branches here and there may poſſibly be ſcorched and conſumed; yet, it cannot be wholly <hi>raked</hi> up in <hi>aſhes, The gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt it,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, in that famous place of <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.18. Where, whatever the conteſt be amongſt interpreters;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Godwin</hi> Moſes and Aaron, <hi>lib.</hi> 5 p. 211</note> this concluſion is beyond all diſpute, That the <hi>Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine</hi> and <hi>councel-boord</hi> of hell (I ſuppoſe I need not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon the known alluſion; in the word <hi>Gates</hi> to the cuſtoms of the Jews) ſhall never be able wholly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and overturn the Church.</p>
            <p>This is alſo an article of the <hi>Creed, I believe the holy Catholick Church,</hi> not that we are hereby engaged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, as the Church believes by an <hi>implicit</hi> Faith;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> it is not, I believe <hi>in</hi> the Church, but, I believe <hi>the</hi> Church to be <hi>Catholick, temporum, perſonarum, &amp; locorum ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> in reſpect of time, perſons and place. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aſted. <hi>Theol. Cate.</hi> p. 352.</note> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there alwaies <hi>was, is,</hi> and <hi>ſhall be</hi> a Church upon earth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I might from hence prove the certain recovery of the Church from outward and inward ſpiritual deſolations;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29487:9"/>but I ſhall wave this, and yet evidence this truth from theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 1. Chriſt is eminently <hi>engaged</hi> for his Churches re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building, and he cannot go back; ſo that we find theſe very engagements do work upon him, when other things will not move him; this is much inſiſted upon by God, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.9, 14, 22. he layes it down as the great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive that turned the ſcales even when he was upon the point of deſtroying Iſrael in Egypt, and in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for their rebellions. <hi>I ſaid I will pour out my fury upon them, but I wrought for my Names ſake,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>earneſtneſs</hi> of the expreſſions and the <hi>repetitions</hi> of them, ſhew that God would have them take notice, that this was the very thing that ſtood betwixt them, and ruine; He is more plain in <hi>Eze.</hi> 36.22. <hi>I do not this for your ſakes O houſe of Iſrael, but for my holy Names ſake, Joſhua</hi> knew the weight of this, when he made it the main argument of his prayer for the people: <hi>And what wilt thou do for thy great name, Joſh.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Samuel</hi> alſo had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement for them upon the ſame ground, 1 Sam. 12.22. <hi>The Lord will not forſake his people for his great Names ſake.</hi> And no wonder if we conſider what theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements are; it is a ſix-fold cord. He is engaged:</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">6. Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on God for repairing the Church.</note> By his <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Oath,</hi> he hath lifted up his hand to Heaven and ſworn, his truth and faithfulneſs lies at the ſtake; when then we have theſe two immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things in which it is impoſſible for God to lye, we cannot want conſolation and aſſurance of this thing. Gods Promiſe and Oath make the thing promiſed to become<note n="*" place="margin">Dominus ipſe fecit ſe debito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, non acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendo, ſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittendo. <hi>Aug. confeſ. lib. 1. cap 4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>debt,</hi> though not ſo much to us, as to<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae ſed ſibi ipſi,</hi> Daven. Juſ. habit. &amp; actual. p. 640.</note> himſelf; and the non-payment of this debt is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with the divine nature. We can then humbly challenge it upon the ſcore of <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> and God himſelf hath put this plea into our mouths; when he tells us that we obtain our faith and eternal life (<hi>called therefore a crown of righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.) from his righteouſneſs and juſtice in <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29487:9"/>promiſes,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1. We read indeed that God doth diſpence ſometime with his <hi>precepts,</hi> but not with <hi>abſolute,</hi> nor yet with <hi>conditional</hi> promiſes (if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions be performed;) and indeed he cannot, except he ſhould ceaſe to be God, <hi>viz.</hi> Holy, Juſt and True, &amp;c. Hence the <hi>School-men</hi> conclude, that ſuch precepts are<note n="*" place="margin">Praetepta in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſabilia ſunt quae ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantur circa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes emanantem ex imagine Dei.</note> 
               <hi>indiſpenſable</hi> (as well as promiſes) whoſe <hi>objects</hi> are things that have an <hi>intrinſecal</hi> goodneſs in them flowing from the <hi>Image</hi> of God, becauſe if he ſhould diſpenſe with theſe he ſhould deny his own Image and himſelf, which is impoſſible; if oaths are ſuch ſacred obligations in the very<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hinc</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Apud Suidam.</note> Judgement of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> that they thought God a ſpecial obſerver and an avenger of their violation; can it be thought that God ſhould forget, or not perform what his own lips have attered!<note n="*" place="margin">Quid eſt Dei veri veraciſque juratio, niſi promiſſi confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mario, &amp; infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium quaedam increpatio? <hi>Aug. civit. Dei lib. 16. cap. 32</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>His oath is enough to eſtabliſh our cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ence, &amp; to check our unbelief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By the ſpecial <hi>intereſt</hi> which he hath in his Church, as Creator of all things, all the world is his, but his own people are his, by a more peculiar title; the wicked belong to him as the <hi>lumber</hi> of his houſe, as the <hi>waſtes</hi> of his demain, as his <hi>veſſels</hi> of diſhonour: his Church is his, not as a mans <hi>goods</hi> are his,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.20.</note> but as a mans <hi>wife,</hi> or <hi>child</hi> is his. He calls it <hi>his ſealed foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, His encloſed garden,</hi> Cant. 4.12. <hi>His choſen people, His people known of all the families of the earth,</hi> Amos 3.2. <hi>His portion, and the lot, or cord of his inheritance,</hi> as the Hebrew hath it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.9. as if he ſhould ſay, I have divided the world by <hi>lot,</hi> and meaſured it by a <hi>cord,</hi> and out of all I have onely choſen my Church, as the <hi>garden</hi> wherein I will <hi>walk,</hi> the <hi>houſe</hi> wherein I will <hi>dwell,</hi> the <hi>ſpouſe</hi> with whom I will <hi>delight</hi> my ſelf.</p>
            <p>All intereſts have not an engaging force; though e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very poſt-head about our houſe, or every ſtake or thorn in our hedge be ours; yet, we do not find our ſelves mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with pitty, or inclined to reſcue them from break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or burning. God himſelf can let the wicked of the world conſume, as the rotten branches of a tree in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29487:10"/>fire, and yet never think himſelf engaged to pluck them out, though they belong to him; <hi>He that made them will not have mercy on them, he that formed them will ſhew them no favour,</hi> Eſa. 27.11. Yet <hi>peculiar intereſts</hi> are <hi>obliging;</hi> this <hi>peculiarity</hi> ariſeth not barely from the <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluteneſs</hi> of dominion and ſoveraignty (for then God ſhould have leſs ſoverainty &amp; dominion over the wicked, who are not his peculiar people) nor from <hi>better natural <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ities</hi> or inclinations in them above others, but from <hi>greater love</hi> and a <hi>deſignment</hi> to a <hi>higher uſe</hi> and <hi>end;</hi> a mans dunghill is as truly his own as his garden, yet ſuch a love hath he to this piece of ground, that he will hedge, dreſs and weed it; when he will not do ſo to the other. The Sanctuary then cannot ſtill lye waſte, he will not give up the inheritance which is ſo peculiarly his own. Chriſts intereſt in the Church is ſo great that it prevails with him to put his own name upon her (as, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. ſo alſo is Chriſt, the head and body are joined in one name, alſo, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.24.) he will ſurely then awake for her. Shall we find our ſelves engaged to help to the utmoſt, when our wife and our child is wronged, and ſhall not God do ſo for his ſons and daughters? Shall he upon the account of intereſt charge us to provide for our Families, and will he neglect his own.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He is yet further engaged, by what he hath already <hi>done</hi> for it; Chriſt bought it at the full rate, he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he gave himſelf for it; he hath preſerved it all along from the beginning, and is at coſt with it every day. If then he had purpoſed to forſake it; would he (as <hi>Manoahs</hi> wife pleaded in another caſe, <hi>Judg,</hi> 13.23.) have done all this for it? What waſte would this have been?</p>
            <p>I find it an ordinary piece of Scripture-Logick to conclude the certainty of mercies deſired, from mercies already beſtowed, becauſe one mercy engageth God to another; thus the Apoſtle argues, <hi>if he have given his Son, will he not together with him give us all things?</hi> Rom.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29487:10"/>8.32. ſo 2 Pet. 1.2, 3. He concludes that grace will be <hi>multiplied,</hi> becauſe he hath <hi>given</hi> the ſeeds and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of it. The argument reſts upon this bottom, <hi>He that hath begun, will alſo perfect.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> This very pleading the Spirit of God makes uſe of in the prayers of his people for the Church, which ſhews it to be very bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtrong: for as God knows the mind of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; So the ſpirit knows the mind of God, and will uſe no argument, which he knows will not prevail. We find <hi>Joſhua</hi> preſſing this upon God, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haſt thou at all brought this people over Jordan? Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſhaphat</hi> urges it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Thou didſt drive out the inhabitants of this Land, and gaveſt it to the ſeed of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham. David</hi> alſo more fully, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.8, 9. <hi>And thou haſt brought a vine out of Egypt, thou haſt caſt out the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and planted it, Why then haſt thou broken down her hedges?</hi> &amp;c. v. 12.</p>
            <p>Yea, it is further to be obſerved, that the <hi>price</hi> we pay, and the <hi>ſufferings,</hi> or hardſhips we undergo for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, doth not onely engage <hi>our honour</hi> to ſee it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; but <hi>our affections alſo.</hi> They ſay,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.25.</note> mothers love thoſe children beſt that put them to moſt pain in the birth; we may ſay that Chriſt <hi>giving</hi> himſelf for his Church, is not onely a <hi>demonſtration</hi> and an effect of <hi>his love,</hi> but alſo a motive and engagement to <hi>a further complacency.</hi> If theſe undertakings of Chriſt for his people had proceeded from <hi>humour,</hi> or <hi>inconſiderate</hi> raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, we might then have feared that the feeling of his ſufferings might have changed his reſolutions;<note n="*" place="margin">Habet omnir amorvim ſuam, nec potest va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care. <hi>Aug. in Pſ. 121.</hi>
               </note> but oh! they were the reſults of an <hi>eternal deliberate</hi> counſel, and managed by a perſon to whom it can never be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, <hi>This man began to build and is not willing, or not able to finiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. By the <hi>love</hi> he carries to it. It is the nature of love to be operative, it cannot be<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Gr. Nazi. car. jamb.</note> idle, it is in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual motion, it ſets the heart on <hi>(a)</hi> fire, and puts on ſtrength and reſolution againſt the greateſt oppoſitions,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29487:11"/>it teacheth the very bruits to expoſe themſelves to dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers for the ſafety of their young ones, and makes the very tame and fearful creatures to be violent and coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious above their ſtrength. We find the little ſparks of our love to be thus powerful upon our ſelves: but what the Ocean of Gods infinite love is, who can comprehend? <hi>Who hath</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Eſa. 40.12.</note> 
               <hi>meaſured the waters in the hollow of his hand? and meated out Heaven with the ſpan?</hi> Though we have no exact ſtandard to meaſure it by; yet, if we look into our ſelves,<note place="margin">Quamvis Deus non cognoſcitur quidditativè, &amp; comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſivè, cognoſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur tamen, viâ negationis, viâ aeminentiae &amp; per operationes ſuas.</note> we can gueſs it to be more then we can ſpeak: we know certainly it is <hi>greater</hi> then ours, more pure, not <hi>ſelf-by-aſſed,</hi> not <hi>pettiſh, fickle,</hi> unconſtant, &amp;c. What a ſtrong engagement muſt that be that ariſeth from an infinitely powerful working love? If we doubt of the certainty, or conſtancy of it, we may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied from his own mouth; he hath ſo fixed the earth that it cannot be moved; and yet his love is more firm, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54.10. <hi>The mountains ſhall depart and the hills be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, but my kindneſs ſhall not depart from thee.</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural affections of the moſt tender-hearted mother to her child, are nothing to this, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.15, 16. <hi>They may forget, yet will not I forget thee, I have graven thee upon the palmes of my hands, thy walls are continually before me;</hi> He cannot look upon <hi>himſelf,</hi> nor upon the <hi>hangings</hi> of Heaven (if I may ſo ſpeak) but he will ſee the names of his people, and muſt remember them. Sing then O Sion, and thou that lieſt in the duſt, the time of thy viſitation will come, becauſe thy God delighteth in thee.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By the <hi>publick declarations</hi> of this love and intereſt in his people, had theſe been onely ſecret <hi>intendments</hi> kept within his own breſt, who could have laid claime to them? Or, if they had not been performed, who could have ſaid to him, <hi>What doſt thou?</hi> But he hath made publick Proclamations of it to the Iſſes afar off, &amp; in the hearing of the Heathen round about. <hi>Moſes</hi> in his prayer takes hold on this, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.14, 15. <hi>The Inhabitants of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29487:11"/>this land have heard that thou, Lord, art among this people, the Nations have heard the fame of thee, and what will they ſay if thou ſhouldſt deſtroy us?</hi> God himſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth that he hath reſpect to this, Eſa. 45.19. <hi>Iſrael ſhall be ſaved in the Lord with an everlaſting Salvation, v.</hi> 17. But what moves God to this? he ſtraightway tells us, <hi>I have not ſpoken in ſecret, in a dark place of the Earth;</hi> my Promiſes were not made in a corner, but openly.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By the <hi>ſcorus, taunts,</hi> and bitter reflections, which the adverſaries would poure upon him if he ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the hedge of his Vineyard to be ſtill trodden down, 1. They would aſperſe him with cruelty, tyranny, and careleſſeneſſe, they would ſay, for miſchiefe <hi>did he bring them out to ſlay them in the mountains,</hi> Exod. 32.12. or 2. With impotency, as if he <hi>could not deliver, becauſe the Lord was not able to bring this people into the land which he ſpake unto them, therefore hath he ſlain them in the wilderneſſe,</hi> Numb. 14.16. Though theſe ſeem to be the objections of profeſſed <hi>Athieſts</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> onely; yet, even people that profeſſe to know God have two much of this in their hearts: we are naturally prone to have hard thoughts of God, when we ſee or feele thoſe diſpenſations that ſeem to be rugged or harſh. <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> her ſelfe is apt to ſay, <hi>the Lord hath forſaken me, and my Lord hath forgotten me,</hi> Eſa. 49.14. 3. There is yet another concluſion which (with more plauſibility, and yet with as much diſtaſt to God) is raiſed from theſe premiſes: they that dare not call Gods power or faithfulneſs into queſtion; yet will they queſtion the truth of the Church; if God ſeem to forſake it, can this be Gods Church (ſay they) thats thus afflicted and toſſed? God lookes upon himſelfe as much concerned in all theſe, he cannot ſuffer his Name to be thus abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and therefore he often reſolves the deliverance of his ſervants, that thereby he might take an occaſion to vindicate both himſelfe and them: how often hear we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29487:12"/>this?<note place="margin">Eſa. 49.23. &amp; 60.16. &amp; 62.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>I will ariſe and they ſhall know that I am the Lord, and they ſhall know that you are my people,</hi> Jer. 30.17. <hi>I will reſtore health unto thee, and I will heal thee of thy wounds, ſaith the Lord, becauſe they called thee an outcaſt, ſaying. This is Zion whom no man ſeeketh after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. As the Church was the <hi>great</hi> thing which God in the Creation of the Word had <hi>an eye</hi> upon, (as a meanes of glorifying himſelfe) ſo is it likewiſe the <hi>main ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of <hi>providence;</hi> had it not been for this, he would not have created the World, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.9, 10. Wee have two things aſſerted by the Apoſtle. 1. <hi>That all things were created by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is the Mediator and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of his Church; and conſequently all this was done in reference to the great deſign of his Church: (I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the place to ſpeak of the Creation of the World, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3. And not of the work of redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though I know many expound it ſo) 2. That he appointed his Church to be the great means of diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Men and Angels, that wonderfull <hi>variety</hi> of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which is more to be ſeen in it then in all the Creation beſides.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And were it not for his Church he would not uphold the world, the righteous are the <hi>pillars</hi> of the earth, he extends indeed his providence to all, even the leaſt and moſt deſpicable things: but he hath a <hi>ſpeciall</hi> care of his Church, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.8. We find Chriſt mounted with his attendants <hi>on red horſes, ſpeckled and white,</hi> that is ready to execute judgement, or mercy, or a mixture of both; the place where he keeps his guards, is ſaid to be <hi>among the Mirtle trees in the bottom</hi> the Mirtle trees figure out unto us the Church, they are low, but preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous plants, the bottom where theſe trees grow, ſhewes us the Churches hazards, ſhe is ſubject to ſtorms, and inundations, but yet Chriſt incamps in the <hi>midſt</hi> of her, in a place moſt <hi>commodious</hi> for the ſuccour and help of every corner, yea and he is on <hi>horſeback,</hi> and <hi>riding</hi> as being in a poſture of ſervice and watchfulneſs for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29487:12"/>their good. To the ſame purpoſe in <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.9. we have mention made of <hi>ſeven eyes</hi> (which in <hi>cap.</hi> 4.10. are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly called <hi>the ſeven eyes of God, which run to and fro through the earth:</hi>) not to trouble you with the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>ſeven,</hi> in a word, theſe eyes are Gods Providence; now obſerve, they are ſaid to be fixed <hi>upon one ſtone,</hi> (that is Jeſus Chriſt the Corner ſtone, and the Church which is built upon it) it ſeems they are very <hi>intent</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church; and yet <hi>cap.</hi> 4. they are ſaid but to <hi>run to and fro,</hi> (not ſo fixedly dwelling) upon all the earth beſide.<note place="margin">1 King. 18.27.</note> If God had been like the blinde careleſſe ſleepy <hi>vanities</hi> of the heathens, or if his Providence had onely kept it ſelfe within the <hi>circuit</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> (as ſome<note place="margin">
                  <p>Epecurei, quae opinio a quibuſdam Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoteli tribui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
                  <p>Si quid in terris curant dii, non niſi maxima curant.</p>
               </note> Philoſophers and others thought, <hi>Job</hi> 22.13, 14.) or if he had onely minded the <hi>greateſt</hi> and <hi>higheſt</hi> matters among the ſons of men (as many have dreamed) then poſſibly the Church might have been neglected: but if his eye<note n="*" place="margin">Job 28.24.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeth under the whole heaven, if he keep and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Vineyard every moment.</hi> Eſa. 27.3. We may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently add the Concluſion of the Prophet, <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>He ſhall cauſe them that come of Jacob to take root, Iſrael ſhall bloſſome and bud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> 3. In the Adminiſtration of Providence, as the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> aim of God is the <hi>good</hi> of his people, ſo the <hi>meanes</hi> which he would rather uſe for bringing it about are <hi>loving kindneſſe and mercies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We are ſure of this, that God intends his Church no hurt, true indeed, take a ſingle affliction (abſtracted from the tendency of Gods deſigne, and the concurrent meanes which muſt bring it about) and it will ſeem to hurt; the thunder and lightnings may affright them, the iron may enter into their ſoules: but view the whole frame, and you will ſee how one wheele turnes about another (like the wheeles of a watch) which (though they have croſſe and contrary motions) all conſpire and<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> work together for good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are as ſure of this alſo, that he rather delights
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29487:13"/>to lead his people with the <hi>cords of love,</hi> and with the <hi>bands</hi> of a <hi>man:</hi> he aſſures us he afflicts not <hi>willingly, Lam.</hi> 3.33. Judgement is his ſtrange worke, believe it, God delights not to be ſtill beating his Children; he will not take up the rod but when he is forced to it, and when nothing elſe will prevail: with what reluctancy and ſtriving doth God chaſtiſe his ſervants, to the very turning of his heart, and the kindling of his repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? Hoſ. 11.8. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up Ephraim?</hi> &amp;c. If then it be the unalterable purpoſe of God to <hi>do good</hi> to his Church, if by afflictions, he doth not <hi>break</hi> down his Sanctuary: but rather <hi>take</hi> it down, as a workman doth with a frame which he intends to ſet up again in better order; (thus he took down <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the <hi>Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> with an intent to build them better, <hi>Jer.</hi> 24.5, 6.) if he delights in the <hi>proſperity</hi> of ſervants, and will not afflict <hi>more</hi> then he <hi>needs</hi> muſt; how chearfully then may we take up that of the Ppophet, Lam. 3.32. <hi>Though he cauſe griefe yet will he have compaſſion, according to the multitude of his mercies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> 4. The <hi>Inſolency</hi> of the <hi>enemy,</hi> upon their ſucceſſes, is exceeding provoking;<note place="margin">Eſa. 10.5, &amp;c.</note> God makes the wicked his rod, his agents, and executioners, in chaſtiſing his children, and withall he ſets them their limits; theſe forget who imloyes them, and preſently <hi>over-act</hi> their Commiſſion: they cannot indeed go a haires breadth beyond Gods <hi>ſecret permiſſion,</hi> yet they can <hi>leape</hi> over the bounds of his <hi>revealled will,</hi> and <hi>moderation;</hi> they can enlarge their boaſtings, and joyn their utmoſt <hi>ſpite,</hi> with their <hi>indeavours,</hi> and proſecute their own <hi>ends</hi> inſtead of Gods. If God ſend the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> againſt an hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Nation, preſently his deſign and thoughts go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the work which God will doe by him; <hi>Eſa.</hi> 10.7. <hi>Howbeit he meaneth not ſo, but it is in his heart to deſtroy, and cut off Nations, not a few;</hi> God takes notice of this, and truly it falls out well for the Church, that their enemies are ſo exceſſive in their rage and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29487:13"/>for this intereſts God in the quarrel of his people. <hi>They ſpeak wickedly concerning oppreſſion, they ſpeak loftily againſt the Church,</hi> and in ſo doing, <hi>they ſet their mouth againſt the heavens,</hi> Pſal. 73.8, 9. Deut. 32.27. God tells us that he is not ſo ſevere againſt his own, as he otherwiſe would be upon this ground, <hi>I would ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them into corners, were it not that I fear the wrath of the enemy: leſt they ſhould behave themſelves ſtrangely,</hi> &amp;c. Again, the adverſaries by their outragious cruelty do but <hi>treaſure</hi> up a <hi>greater</hi> vengeance for themſelves. <hi>Obad. v.</hi> 10.12. <hi>For thy violence againſt thy brother Jacob, ſhame ſhall cover thee; thou ſhouldeſt not have looked on the day of thy Brother,</hi> &amp;c. Likewiſe, <hi>Zach,</hi> 1.15. <hi>I am very ſore diſpleaſed with the heathen that are at eaſe, for I was but a little diſpleaſed</hi> (with Sion) <hi>and they helped forward the affliction;</hi> this made loſſe of children and widow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to come upon <hi>Babilon,</hi> in their perfection, <hi>in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in one day,</hi> Eſa. 47.6, 8. <hi>Becauſe I was wrath with my people, and thou did ſhew them no mercy;</hi> can God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to hear the <hi>ſhoutings</hi> of <hi>Edom,</hi> when they cry,<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.7.</note> 
               <hi>raſe it, raſe it even to the ground?</hi> can he ſee them <hi>clap</hi> the <hi>hand,</hi> and <hi>wag</hi> the <hi>head</hi> over Sion in miſery? can he (think you) ſuffer the brags of the wicked, when they ſay, our <hi>hand</hi> is <hi>high, By the ſtrength of my hand have I done it?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32 27. Eſa. 10.13.15.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall the axe boaſt it ſelfe againſt him that hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth therewith? or ſhall the ſawe magnifie it ſelfe againſt him that ſhaketh it?</hi> the Husband may ſome time be diſpleaſed with his wife, but if any other ſhall upon this ground beat or revile her, this will make the husband and the wife agree again, and ſet them both with joynt indignation againſt the forwardneſs of the other partie; the greateſt oppoſers the Church hath, ſhall do this kindneſs for her, (in diſpite of their hearts,) even when they think to do moſt againſt her.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>5</label> 5. Nothing can <hi>hinder</hi> deliverance, when God will work indeed; it may be in this, as it is with the heart of a man in the work of coverſion, he may reſiſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29487:14"/>
               <hi>ſtruglingly,</hi> but not <hi>conqueringly;</hi> the Divell and men may <hi>oppoſe</hi> Gods deſign, but <hi>overturn</hi> it they cannot.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Power cannot prevaile;</hi> though they unite all their ſtrength and utmoſt forces, yet ſhall they be aſhamed; aſſemble your ſelves, and you ſhall be broken: hath man an arme like God?<note place="margin">Eſa. 27.4.</note> 
               <hi>who then will ſet bryars and thorns againſt him in battell? will he not go through them, and burn them together?</hi> the attempts of men againſt God will as little prevaile, as the <hi>ſhoutings of ſhepherds upon a Lion roaring upon his prey;</hi> You have the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 31.4, 5. When a multitude of <hi>ſhepherds is called forth againſt him, he will not be afraid of their voice, nor abaſe himſelfe for the noiſe of them: ſo ſhall the Lord of Hoſts come down to fight for Mount Sion, and for the hill thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Though Policy ſhould be joyned to power, yet all would not ſerve;</hi> that this will do more then ſtrength ſometimes, is teſtified by multitudes of inſtances, <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine de Medices</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> uſed to ſay, She could do more againſt the Proteſtants with a <hi>ſheet of paper,</hi> then with an Army: but God can look through their plots, and make their own counſells caſt them down; <hi>while they be folded together as thorns, they ſhall be devoured as ſtubble fully dry,</hi> Nahum 1.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Neither will pitty prevail with God;</hi> if the lives and ſafety of a whole Nation ſtand in the way of his peoples good, he thinks it nothing to throw them all away for his Church: he will reprove Kings for their ſakes; what is it to him to ranſom his ſervants with the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Kingdomes? Eſa. 43.3. <hi>I gave</hi> Egypt <hi>for thy ranſome,</hi> Ethiopia, <hi>and</hi> Seba <hi>for thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>6</label> 6. The reeſtabliſhment and flouriſhing ſtate of his Church, is a <hi>neceſſary conſequence</hi> of the <hi>promiſes</hi> which <hi>God the Father</hi> made to Chriſt as <hi>Mediatour;</hi> theſe are reckoned up under ſeverall heads, by<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rutherford,</hi> Cov. of grace Part. 2. cap. 11.</note> ſome: I ſhall not need to inſiſt upon them largely: not only was a <hi>ſeed</hi> promiſed, <hi>he ſhall ſee his ſeed,</hi> and that a numerous off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29487:14"/>(by profeſſion) <hi>Nations which knew not thee ſhall run unto thee,</hi> Eſa. 55.5. <hi>Many Nations ſhall be joyned unto the Lord, Zach.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Bleſſed be Egypt my people</hi> (ſhall God ſay) <hi>and Aſſyria the work of my hands,</hi> Eſa. 19.24. but alſo victory over the enemies of the Church; Eſa. 53.12. <hi>I will devide him a portion with the great, and he ſhall divide the ſpoil with the ſtrong, his Dominion ſhall be from ſea to ſea,</hi> Zach. 9, 10. Yea further, there are promiſes of <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> given to Chriſt <hi>particularly reſpecting</hi> the <hi>building</hi> of his Church, Eſay 49.8. <hi>In a day of ſalvation have I helped thee, I will preſerve thee</hi> (not ſo much in reference to his Perſon, as to his Church and Kingdom; ſo Diodate, and others expound) <hi>to eſtabliſh the earth, and to cauſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the deſolate heritages;</hi> alſo Eſa. 42.6. and many places more.</p>
            <p>Why then are our hearts troubled?<note place="margin">Zach. 9.11.</note> what though we be <hi>priſoners in a pit where is not water?</hi> what if we be as <hi>dryed bones ſcattered upon the</hi> earth? ſhall we not live? let us caſt the buſineſs upon Chriſt with a holy careleſſnes, (pardon the expreſſion) <hi>let him ſee to it;</hi> his Church cannot fall,<note place="margin">ſi ruimus nos ruit &amp; Chriſtus <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Luther.</note> but he muſt fall firſt; yea, the Father muſt then be <hi>unfaithfull</hi> to Chriſt; for how can that be <hi>fulfilled</hi> which God hath <hi>promiſed</hi> to him, if the Church be <hi>ſtill covered with a cloud in</hi> anger, if ſhe <hi>ſtill</hi> be <hi>ſolitary as a</hi> widow, or, if the <hi>wayes of Zion do ſtill mourne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe 6 evidences do (as I ſuppoſe) fully clear the firſt branch of the Doctrine, the ſecond (which I am next to ſpeak to) is,</p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>worke (when it comes to be accompliſhed,) ſhall be very glorious; let us</hi> look a little into this,<note place="margin">The ſecond Branch of the Doctrine.</note> and we ſhall find ſeverall things concurring to make up the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>former</hi> miſery of the Church will add no ſmall <hi>luſtre</hi> to its building: its formere tears, blackneſs, and deſolations ſhall now make it more beautifull; what a change ſhall that be? when ſhe that was caſt our as <hi>the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29487:15"/>filth</hi> and <hi>off-ſcouring</hi> of all <hi>things;</hi> ſhe whom <hi>no eye pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> againſt <hi>whom every</hi> tongue let looſe the <hi>bridle,</hi> and uttered diſdainfull taunts, and cruell revilings; is now <hi>advanced</hi> to the <hi>throne,</hi> and her <hi>head</hi> lift up above her <hi>enemies</hi> round about? Crowns and Scepters are but ſmal advancements to one that is already but a little below them; tis but one remove, but for one that but now <hi>embraced</hi> the dunghill, to be called <hi>to ſit above Princes,</hi> this is much! tis a great deale more for <hi>Joſeph</hi> to come from the priſon to be next to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or, for <hi>Merdecai</hi> to come from the gate to the Kings Robes, then for thoſe that are great already to be advanced a little above their preſent dignities.</p>
            <p>This will not <hi>highten</hi> the glory of the Church of the <hi>admiration</hi> and <hi>envy</hi> of their adverſaries, but it will alſo <hi>ſweeten</hi> their <hi>former afflictions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3.19.20.</note> and their <hi>preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance;</hi> the wormwood and the gall they are bitter in the taſt, yet ſweet to the remembrance afterward; when Sion is reſtored, it will be pleaſant to review and look back upon her late preſſures, ſhe can then with delight remember the <hi>waters of</hi> Babylon, where ſhe ſat and wept; they that afore time were wont to wag the head and clap their hands, ſaying, Is this the City <hi>that men call</hi> the <hi>perfection of</hi> beauty?<note place="margin">Lam. 2.15.</note> ſhall now turne their tune, and ſay, Is this the City that was <hi>troden</hi> down and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed? the Children of God ſhall alſo with teares of Joy and mutuall <hi>congratulations,</hi> compare their reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with their old calamities,<note place="margin">Hag. 2.4.</note> inverting that of <hi>Haggai, Who is there left among among us that ſaw this houſe in her former Deſolations, and how do we ſee it now? this is the Lords doing and it is marvellous in our eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Great</hi> will be the <hi>hight</hi> of its <hi>advancement,</hi> it will not be an ordinary building, the Promiſes which are made to the New-Teſtament-Church ſpeak of <hi>great</hi> things, Eſa. 22. Micha 4.1. <hi>In the laſt dayes it ſhall come to paſs that the mountain of the houſe of the Lord ſhall be eſtabliſhed, in the top of the Mountains, it ſhall be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29487:15"/>exalted above the hills.</hi> 1. Its exaltation ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous to the eyes of all. 2. It ſhall have a <hi>tryumphing</hi> glory after <hi>mountanous</hi> difficulties. 3. A glory above <hi>worldly ſtates</hi> and kingdomes (which are called moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and hills, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.15, 16) 4.<note place="margin">Diodate &amp; Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius in loc.</note> A well <hi>bottomed</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, not overturned by every tempeſt of oppoſition, though like a City on an hill, it be very obnoxious to winds and ſtorms; all theſe ſeem to be pointed at in the next Text.</p>
            <p>And indeed, if we conſider; 1. The <hi>power, skill</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> of the work-man (God) to his Church, or 2. the <hi>preparations</hi> he makes for this building, in <hi>hewing</hi> and <hi>dreſſing</hi> the materials; we may well expect a glorious Fabrick, <hi>a Palace of ſilver,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>nothing mean can come from his hands;</hi> much leſs can he be guilty of pompous <hi>trif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> or of making a great ſhew, and bringing forth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (like the birth of the mountains in <hi>Aeſop</hi>) 3. If God ſhould do no more but <hi>ſcowr</hi> off the <hi>filth,</hi> which his people contract by <hi>lying</hi> among <hi>the pots,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.13.</note> their native <hi>beauty</hi> would make them ſhine like the <hi>wings</hi> of a <hi>dove;</hi> Who can expreſs what a pleaſing ſight it would be to ſee the Church in its naked glory? Now when God reſtores her, he doth not onely take off the <hi>vails</hi> of <hi>perſecution</hi> and <hi>diſtemper</hi> (in a great part) which did much obſcure her; but, fourthly, he gives ſome <hi>remarkable addition</hi> to her glory; if you caſt your eye <hi>backward</hi> upon the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>changes</hi> that have happened to the Church, you will find that when he hath turned to her, he not onely ſet her where ſhe was <hi>before:</hi> but <hi>advanced</hi> her eſtate <hi>above</hi> her former proſperity; and if we look before us, we ſhall find in the <hi>womb</hi> of the promiſes <hi>more</hi> glory <hi>entailed</hi> upon the Church, then yet ſhe hath <hi>enjoyed:</hi> and this to be brought forth after the great <hi>hour</hi> of <hi>temptation,</hi> that ſhall come to <hi>try</hi> the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of the earth, upon the riſing again of the witneſſes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.11. Theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes (I forbear to mention them) in the Old and New Teſtament, though they do not win me to the <hi>Millenaries</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:29487:16"/>opinion, about the perſonal reign of Chriſt on earth a thouſand years: yet, this ſeems to me an undoubted <hi>truth</hi> from them; that the Church ſhall be <hi>more</hi> glorious then <hi>heretofore,</hi> in <hi>holineſs, unity, peace, numerouſneſs</hi> and <hi>conqueſt</hi> of her enemies.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>unexpectedneſs</hi> of the change (when God turns the captivity of his people) will be a very <hi>conſiderable</hi> circumſtance to heighten their glory; <hi>ſuddenneſs</hi> aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates <hi>grief</hi> and <hi>joy.</hi> When the Church was freed from the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> captivity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.1. it was ſo unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and wonderful, <hi>That they were like thoſe that dream:</hi> though they hoped for it; yet they could ſcarce believe it when it was come, their deliverance ſeemed rather a <hi>dream</hi> then a <hi>realty;</hi> this <hi>filled their mouth with laughter, and their tongue with ſinging.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>ſeaſonableneſs</hi> of it ſets the glory yet a <hi>ſtep</hi> higher; among men the <hi>ſeaſonableneſs</hi> of their favours is almoſt the very <hi>eſſence</hi> of them, that which comes <hi>out</hi> of ſeaſon, often doth no more then ſhew the <hi>good will</hi> of thoſe that pity us; but proves not <hi>helpful:</hi> what is <hi>phyſick,</hi> or a <hi>pardon</hi> to a man that is <hi>dead?</hi> Had they come in time they might have done good. God never miſſeth the right ſeaſon; he that requires of us <hi>fruits in ſeaſon,</hi> will not do his own works <hi>out</hi> of ſeaſon; he that waits to be <hi>gracious,</hi> and ſtayes for the <hi>fitteſt</hi> oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſhewing mercy, will not <hi>neglect</hi> it when it preſents it ſelf; it is Gods deſign to put an honour upon <hi>all</hi> his <hi>waies</hi> and <hi>works,</hi> and therefore when we wax <hi>wanton</hi> and undervalue his bleſſings, he takes them <hi>away:</hi> till the <hi>bitterneſs</hi> of affliction makes us <hi>prize</hi> and and <hi>reliſh</hi> them better: it is his deſign alſo to make our troubles to carry a <hi>juſt proportion</hi> to our <hi>ſtrength;</hi> he will not inflict <hi>too</hi> much at <hi>once</hi> leaſt we be overwhelmed;<note place="margin">Eſa 57.16.</note> nor continue it <hi>too long</hi> leaſt the <hi>ſpirits ſhould fail before</hi> him, and <hi>the Souls that he hath made;</hi> hence is it that he brings his people to the <hi>pits brink</hi> and <hi>then</hi> delivers them: ſo <hi>far</hi> he carries them, that they might ſee the <hi>worth</hi> of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29487:16"/>their deliverance, and the <hi>ſeaſonableneſs</hi> of their eſcape: and no <hi>further,</hi> becauſe he intends not to <hi>deſtroy</hi> them.</p>
            <p>How ſeaſonable is meat to the fainting Soul? Even <hi>unſavory</hi> and <hi>bitter</hi> things are precious and <hi>ſweet</hi> to the hungry; how <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> and glorious is deliverance to a Church <hi>waſted</hi> and <hi>deſolate?</hi> When his ſervant are ready to ſay, <hi>The Lord hath forgotten to be gracious;</hi> or as <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.17, 18. <hi>Thou haſt removed my Soul far off from peace, I forgat proſperity, and I ſaid, My ſtrength and my hope is periſhed from the Lord; Then</hi> for God to <hi>ſtep</hi> in betwixt <hi>them</hi> and <hi>diſpair,</hi> and ſo ſeaſonably to recover them, when they give <hi>all</hi> for <hi>loſt,</hi> how <hi>glorious</hi> a mercy is it?</p>
            <p n="5">5. God will do his work in a <hi>glorious way,</hi> the <hi>manner</hi> and means will be <hi>miraculous</hi> and <hi>wonderful;</hi> thus he brought Iſrael out of the <hi>houſe of bondage,</hi> with <hi>ſigns</hi> and <hi>wonder,</hi> and in after times (though the Church cannot expect the very <hi>ſame</hi> miracles of <hi>killing</hi> the firſt born of their enemies, <hi>dividing</hi> the red Sea, &amp;c.) yet, God hath promiſed he will ſet thoſe <hi>before</hi> him as his <hi>pattern;</hi> and that there ſhall be ſome <hi>reſemblance</hi> and <hi>correſpondency</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt their deliverances, &amp; that out of Egypt, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.15. <hi>According to the dayes of thy coming out of the land of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt will I ſhew unto him marvellous things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David,</hi> when he returns thanks to God for delivering him out of the hand of all his enemies, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.8, 9,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Dickſon,</hi> on Pſal. 18.</note> &amp;c. he alludes to the moſt glorious <hi>manifeſtations</hi> of God in the behalf of his people, as if they were the <hi>ſame</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles acted <hi>over again,</hi> which God ſhewed; 1. At <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai</hi> in giving the Law, <hi>The earth ſhook and trembled,</hi> &amp;c. v. 8. 2. At the <hi>battel</hi> againſt the five Kings, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10.11. whom God overthrew with hail-ſtones, <hi>The Lord thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ut of Heaven, he ſent forth his arrows and ſcattered them,</hi> v. 14. And 3. at the <hi>red ſea, The channels of water were ſeen,</hi> &amp;c. v. 15. If <hi>David,</hi> being but one ſingle perſon, finds in his deliverances ſomething <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:29487:17"/>thoſe noble act of God, much <hi>more</hi> may the Church: and if Gods waies were ſeriouſly <hi>ſtudied,</hi> we ſhould find wonders and miracles in <hi>every</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p n="6">6. God will <hi>raiſe</hi> the Glory of his enterprize upon the <hi>confuſion</hi> and <hi>aſtoniſhment</hi> of his adverſaries; it was the cuſtome of the <hi>Romanes</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> to reſerve many of their <hi>Captives</hi> to augment the glory of their <hi>triumphs.</hi> Thus will God do, when he will redeem Zion, he will give the ſtout adverſaries as <hi>duſt to their ſword, and as driven ſtubble to their bow.</hi> He will make them <hi>ariſe and threſh the mountains,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 41.2, 15.</note> 
               <hi>and beat the hills as chaff;</hi> where will then be the glory of their proud looks? This is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently ſet forth in <hi>Mich</hi> 7.10, 16. When God brings his ſervants to the light; <hi>Then ſhe that is mine enemy ſhall ſee it, and ſhame ſhall cover her;</hi> which ſaid, <hi>Where is the Lord thy God. The Nations ſhall ſee and be confounded at all their might, they ſhall lay their hand upon their mouth; their ears ſhall be deaf, they ſhall lick the duſt like a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent: they ſhall move out of their holes, like wormes of the earth: they ſhall be afraid of the Lord our God, and ſhall fear becauſe of thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. There is one thing more which will beautify the Church when God comes to plead her cauſe, ſhe ſhall (beſide what is <hi>inherent</hi>) have a <hi>derivative</hi> glory; a ray of the beauty and majeſty of Chriſt her Lord and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſhall be upon her, as <hi>Moſes</hi> his face became <hi>ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> by Convereſing with God. It is true the Church hath no beauty which is not <hi>borrowed,</hi> ſhe is <hi>comely</hi> by the <hi>comelineſs which</hi> Chriſt <hi>puts upon her;</hi> but this is a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diancy <hi>occaſional</hi> and for the <hi>time,</hi> begetting a greater <hi>reverance</hi> and <hi>awe</hi> from her adverſaries; this ſeems to be ſpoken of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.17. <hi>Let the beauty of the Lord our God be upon us;</hi> and <hi>Eſa.</hi> 4.5. <hi>I will create upon every dwelling place in mount Sion, and upon her aſſemblies a cloud and ſmoak by day, and the ſhining of a flaming fire by night, and upon all the glory ſhall be a defence.</hi> Where God
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29487:17"/>alludes to the <hi>pillar</hi> of fire, and his glory coming <hi>down</hi> upon the <hi>Tabernacle;</hi> that as in thoſe glorious appearances the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> did <hi>ſhine</hi> with the glory of God; So ſhould his Church, when he appears gloriouſly in it: and this ſhall highten the <hi>admiration</hi> of the ſpirits of men towards his people.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>third</hi> thing comes now to be ſpoken to;<note place="margin">The third Branch of the Doctrine.</note> 
               <hi>viz. That whoever be the inſtrument, yet the chief honour of the work is Chriſts;</hi> this will be eaſily cleared.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Father <hi>committed</hi> this <hi>work,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> power to manage it into <hi>Chriſts</hi> hand, <hi>Matth</hi> 28.18. <hi>All power is given to me in Heaven and in earth;</hi> to Chriſt as <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> belongs <hi>ſole, ſupreme</hi> and <hi>abſolute</hi> authority for the <hi>gathering, upholding</hi> and <hi>governing</hi> his Church; and hence he gives encouragement and commiſſion to the Apoſtles, to go and preach, <hi>Go ye therefore and teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> v. 19. I need not here trouble that Queſtion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>twofold</hi> Kingdome of Chriſt, <hi>as God,</hi> and <hi>as Mediator;</hi> or whether <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> be from Chriſt as <hi>head</hi> of the Church;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gilleſpy,</hi> Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons Rod. lib. 2. cap. 6. <hi>Iranes.</hi>
               </note> it is enough to our preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to take what is already <hi>granted</hi> by <hi>all:</hi> that the Mediator is <hi>God equal</hi> with the Father, and ſo Rules o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all, and as <hi>God-man</hi> he hath a leaſt <hi>all Eccleſiaſtical</hi> power, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Kingly Government;</hi> Yea, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a power</hi> and <hi>over-ruling</hi> Providence, by which he can <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> of all things; for his glory and his Churches good, this will prove the building of the Temple to be his work, and then it is eaſy to infer that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the glory of it is his alſo.</p>
            <p>Men, indeed, are inſtruments in this employment, and they are ſtiled <hi>fellow-workers,</hi> but they can do nothing <hi>alone,</hi> no more then the tool can work without the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and if they could (yet ſeeing they are but ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants) Chriſt hath the honour of <hi>all</hi> that is done <hi>by</hi> them,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.22.</note> and that upon a more <hi>unqueſtionable account</hi> then the victories of <hi>David</hi> ſervants are <hi>aſcribed</hi> to <hi>David</hi> himſelf, <hi>not unto us</hi> (let his ſervants ſay) <hi>but to thy name be the praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:29487:18"/>
            <p n="2">2. The glorious <hi>perfection</hi> which he <hi>brings</hi> his work unto, ſhews it to be beyond the power or skill of <hi>men</hi> and <hi>Angels.</hi> We may perceive the <hi>traces</hi> of infinite power, wiſdom and love, in <hi>every parcel</hi> and <hi>piece</hi> of it, much more then when we ſee the whole <hi>frame</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Church reparation is the creating of <hi>new</hi> Heavens &amp; <hi>new</hi> Earth, and who will aſcribe ſuch a thing to man? In <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54.11. he declares the ſtate of his reſtored Church thus: <hi>I will lay thy ſtones with fair colours, and thy foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations with Saphirs, I will make thy windows of Agates and thy gates of Carbuncles,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe expreſſions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the Church to a building made up all of precious ſtones, with curious art and contrivement. We do not uſe to father <hi>exact</hi> pieces upon <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>impotence,</hi> and we may as well attribute the building of our <hi>Caſtles</hi> and <hi>Palaces</hi> to <hi>birds</hi> and <hi>flies,</hi> as the <hi>eſtabliſhment</hi> and <hi>beauty</hi> of the Church to <hi>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He doth this <hi>quickly</hi> as in a <hi>moment;</hi> you may know by his <hi>pace</hi> that it is not the <hi>goings</hi> of a man,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.8.</note> but of him that <hi>rides upon the wings of the wind, Who comes leaping upon the mountains and ſcipping upon the hills.</hi> He can quickly blaſt the greatneſs of men, and as quickly lift up from the earth him that was fallen if ye doubt of this, conſider how quickly and eaſily the Heaven and Earth were created, and how ſuddenly it ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed at laſt! though God ſeems to delay deliverance for a time (as the ſence of the burthen makes it ſeem a longer time to the afflicted then it is) yet when he ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, he will make a quick diſpatch; peace is a work of <hi>Creation, Behold I create peace,</hi> &amp;c. and Creation takes not up <hi>much</hi> time, it is done in an inſtant; the Lord calls us out to wonder at this, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66.8. <hi>Who hath heard ſuch a thing? Who bath ſeen ſuch a thing? Shall the earth be made to bring forth in one day? Or ſhall a Nation be born at once? For as ſoon as Sion travelled ſhe brought forth her children;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Veni, Vidi, Vici.</note> He makes more haſt then if corn ſhould come to <hi>maturity</hi> the <hi>ſame</hi> day it was ſown, &amp;c. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29487:18"/>Caeſars</hi> ſwift conqueſts are nothing to the conqueſts of him that doth but <hi>ſpeak</hi> and it is <hi>done;</hi> it muſt then be ſtupendous <hi>ignorance</hi> or <hi>arrogancy</hi> that gives not Chriſt the honour of ſuch actions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He brings his work through <hi>viſible contradictions</hi> and <hi>unlikelyhoods,</hi> Eſa. 43.19. <hi>I will make a way in the Wilderneſs, and rivers in the Deſart;</hi> and in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.15. He promiſeth to give her vine yards from the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>I will bring her into the Wilderneſs, and will give her her vine-yards from thence;</hi> Surely, the barren heath of the Wilderneſs is an unlikely place to make a vine-yard of: ſo we read <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.13. <hi>He made them to ſuck ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney out of the rock, and oyl out of the flinty rock.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Burroughs,</hi> Hoſ. p. 501.</note> Not that honey and oyl came out of the rock as the waters did, after the ſmiting of <hi>Moſes:</hi> but that they had their ſweetneſs and comforts <hi>where,</hi> and from <hi>whence, They might leaſt expect them:</hi> out of <hi>rocky difficulties,</hi> all ages have given teſtimony to this, the <hi>wounds</hi> of the Church, the <hi>poyſonous</hi> arrows of adverſaries, the <hi>apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſies</hi> of the wicked, <hi>diſſentions, martyrdoms, every</hi> thing that ſeemed to deſtroy have been <hi>bended</hi> about (contrary to the intendments of men) to further the Churches more <hi>laſting</hi> peace and happineſs. We our ſelves have ſeen that the ſtorm that threatned our ruine hath caſt us <hi>upon a rock,</hi> where we have a greater ſecurity from the <hi>waves,</hi> a <hi>ſafer</hi> ſtanding, the great ſhip-wrack of Faith and Conſcience that many have made; hath <hi>diſcovered</hi> hypocrites, <hi>manifeſted</hi> who are fincere, puts men on <hi>unity,</hi> ſhews the neceſſity of <hi>Church diſcipline</hi> and <hi>government,</hi> with the <hi>reſtraint</hi> of licentious opinions and practices, hath occaſioned the <hi>clearing</hi> and <hi>vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of truths, and hath <hi>quickened</hi> and <hi>cautioned</hi> both Miniſters and people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> argues from the ſtrange and unuſual death of <hi>Corah,</hi> that it was not chance but Gods immediate hand, that deſtroyed thoſe Rebels, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.29, 30. And ſo may we in this caſe ſay, God is ſeen in the <hi>ſtrangeneſs</hi> of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29487:19"/>his workings, the <hi>dulleſt</hi> heads, the moſt <hi>envious</hi> hearts ſhall acknowledg his finger, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.20. <hi>The Beaſts of the field ſhall honour me, the dragg us and the owles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I give waters in the wilderneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.3. Pſal. 68.34.</note> much more ſhall his People aſcribe greatneſſe to God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He doth all this for his Church, when ſhe hath the <hi>feweſt helpers;</hi> when <hi>lover</hi> and <hi>friend forſakes</hi> her, nay, when friends <hi>wound</hi> her, when they that ſhould make <hi>up</hi> her <hi>breaches,</hi> make them <hi>wider,</hi> when the <hi>keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of the <hi>wall</hi> ſmite her, and take away <hi>her vail;</hi> Tis the deſign of God, that in works of this nature <hi>little</hi> of man ſhould be ſeen, leaſt he ſhould ſay <hi>mine own wiſdom</hi> and <hi>ſtrength hath done it;</hi> and often he lets them <hi>weary</hi> themſelves in their own endeavours, and <hi>then</hi> when they ſee they can do nothing: he appears with this acknowledgment from all; <hi>Lord, thou haſt wrought all our works in us,</hi> Eſa. 63.5. <hi>I looked and there was none to help, therefore mine own harm brought Salvation;</hi> The Glory then of this deliverance is Chriſts.</p>
            <p>I have now brought you to the <hi>fourth</hi> Branch of the Doctrine.<note place="margin">Branch 4. Of the Doctrine.</note> 
               <hi>This work ſhall then be done, when peace ſhall poſſeſſe the Church by the Power of Government and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Peace</hi> of the Church is the <hi>accompliſhment</hi> and <hi>completement</hi> of this building; all the conflicts, battells, deſolations, and conqueſts of the Church, they are but the <hi>noiſe</hi> of the <hi>axe,</hi> and <hi>hammer</hi> fitting and <hi>ſquaring</hi> the matereialls; but when the <hi>Temple</hi> is built, the noiſe of them <hi>ceaſeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Peace is the <hi>end</hi> and <hi>aime</hi> of God, in all the <hi>preparations</hi> he makes for this building.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Tis the great <hi>ſubject</hi> of the Promiſes made to the Church, and ſometime whatever concerns the happineſſe of Sion, is <hi>wrapt</hi> up in that word, <hi>great ſhall be the peace of thy children,</hi> Eſa. 54.13. <hi>Behold I will extend Peace to her like a River.</hi> Eſa. 66.12. and many places more.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:29487:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But <hi>What Peace</hi> is requiſite to make up Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-reparation?</p>
            <p>Anſ. 1. <hi>There muſt be outward Peace;</hi> Peace from ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries round about; when God makes the deſtroyer to ceaſe, and gives his Churches reſt; for while it is <hi>Perſecuted,</hi> the Sanctuary is ſaid to be <hi>trodden down;</hi> this is the building of the <hi>outer wall,</hi> and fence, which preſerves the <hi>tender plants</hi> from the <hi>violence</hi> of the wild hoare, and gives <hi>opportunity</hi> and <hi>advantage</hi> for growth; the Church indeed will <hi>thrive</hi> and increaſe under afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſometime, and that not only in the <hi>root,</hi> in <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>ſolidity,</hi> but alſo in the <hi>branches,</hi> in its <hi>extent</hi> and <hi>number;</hi> thus we read in the <hi>Acts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 12.24. &amp; 5.14.</note> while the Apoſtles were impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned and forbidden to ſpeak in the Name of Chriſt, that the Word of the <hi>Lord grew exceedingly, and many were added to the Church, multitudes both of men</hi> and <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> but the <hi>greateſt</hi> ſeaſon of growing is, when the ſtorme is <hi>over,</hi> for then the Word of the Lord <hi>prevails mightily,</hi> and (like the heat of the Sun after Winter) <hi>invites</hi> thoſe plants to <hi>appear,</hi> which the <hi>froſt</hi> kept <hi>und er</hi> ground, thoſe which we call <hi>growing ſickneſſes,</hi> do not appear to be ſo, till the ſickneſs is <hi>over,</hi> for then the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhoot up in length, ſo that we may better aſcribe the growing to <hi>health</hi> then to <hi>ſickneſſe;</hi> when peace is abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it <hi>fills</hi> the Church with <hi>corrupt humours, formality, neglect, hypocriſie,</hi> &amp;c. and then God <hi>purges</hi> it by <hi>afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and after the humours are <hi>evacuated,</hi> then he ſends <hi>peace</hi> again, that it may increaſe, as the <hi>tender graſſe ſpringing out of the earth by clear ſhining after rain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>There muſt be inward Peace,</hi> for this is the maine, the <hi>inteſtine</hi> diviſions of the Church do it more <hi>harme,</hi> then the <hi>ſword</hi> of the Enemy; a ſpirit of <hi>giddineſſe</hi> and <hi>confuſion</hi> will do more to <hi>waſte</hi> it, then fire and ſword can doe; <hi>floating bottels</hi> will ſooner break by their <hi>own claſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> then by the <hi>violence</hi> of the <hi>waves</hi> alone. I might
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29487:20"/>here tell you the ſtories of the Primitive times, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> work did <hi>Arrianiſme,</hi> &amp;c. make? for the Cure of this the Lord promiſeth the bleſſing of <hi>unity</hi> and <hi>concord,</hi> which is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of heart,</hi> when a Spirit of love animates them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of way,</hi> when the Lord <hi>is one,</hi> and his Name <hi>one,</hi> when they ſerve him with <hi>one lip,</hi> and <hi>one ſhoulder, they ſhall be of one heart, and of one way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>This unity muſt ariſe from Government and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> tis not <hi>every</hi> confederacy or combination that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paires the Church; even Theeves and <hi>Pirates</hi> have a <hi>kind</hi> of unity among themſelves; Peace (if it be right) muſt be in conjunction with holineſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such a Peace is <hi>well grounded,</hi> tis of the right kinde, when it beares Gods <hi>image</hi> and <hi>ſuperſcription,</hi> it ſhould leane upon the <hi>baſis</hi> of <hi>Divine</hi> Inſtitution, not on the <hi>ſtaffe</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the broken reed of <hi>humane</hi> Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and policy, and this declares the Conqueſt to be of God, not of man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Tis <hi>well guarded,</hi> and more laſting, whatſoever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth not from this ground, hath the <hi>principles</hi> of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion <hi>in it ſelfe,</hi> and cannot be kept up long.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This is <hi>a growing</hi> peace, a peace that hath a <hi>ſeed</hi> in it ſelfe, which though in the beginning it be <hi>ſmll,</hi> yet its latter end ſhall <hi>greatly</hi> increaſe; tis glorious in its <hi>firſt</hi> riſing, but like the Sun it will <hi>ſhine clearly even unto the perfect day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It mutually <hi>gives</hi> to, and <hi>receives</hi> advantage from holineſſe, holineſſe is that which <hi>becomes Gods ſervants and houſe for ever,</hi> tis the beauty of them; Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Ordinances <hi>procure</hi> peace, for tis their end to <hi>weede</hi> out of the Vineyard whatever may <hi>offend,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and beat down every <hi>root</hi> of bitterneſſe, it ariſeth from order, and doth preſerve it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:29487:20"/>
               <head>Application</head>
               <p>You have heard the Doctrine explained and opened: I ſhall now bring it nearer to you by drawing forth thoſe practicall <hi>inferences</hi> which it will afford us.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> 1. The Enemy hath no cauſe to <hi>infult</hi> over the Church when ſhe is in <hi>diſtreſſe,</hi> ſeeing he that hath <hi>ſmitten will certainly heal it;</hi> though he hide his face <hi>a little</hi> while, yet he will <hi>return</hi> with <hi>everlaſting compaſſions;</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not your ſelves ye infulting foes, ye ſhall not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh your deſign, tis not in your Power to <hi>reverſe</hi> the decrees of heaven; <hi>The Viſion will ſpeak in its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time, and will not lie,</hi> Mich. 7.8. <hi>Rejoyce not againſt me O mine Enemy: when I fall I ſhall ariſe; when I fit in darkneſſe, the Lord ſhall be a light unto me;</hi> nay, know that the time will come when you ſhall <hi>eat</hi> your ſpiteful words, and diſdainfull ſpeeches; they are upon <hi>record</hi> in Gods book: he forgets them not; all your <hi>greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>ſplendor</hi> will not keep God from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>a ſtepping-ſtone</hi> of you, and laying you in the <hi>dirt;</hi> nay, God will make you <hi>inſtruments</hi> (though againſt your will,) to helpe on that work, which you ſo much <hi>oppoſe;</hi> you are but Gods <hi>Pionneeres,</hi> to digg up the rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh, and to make way for the foundation: He that can make the <hi>wrath</hi> of man to <hi>praiſe</hi> him, will bring good out of all the evil you intend to do; take heed, you prepare a ſcourge for your ſelves; <hi>Jeruſalem ſhall be a burdenſome ſtone, all that burden themſelves with it ſhall be cut in pieces,</hi> Zach. 12.3.</p>
               <p>What God may do with his Church in <hi>England,</hi> I cannot now enquire, to determine whether our <hi>hopes</hi> will out weigh our <hi>feares,</hi> would ask a longer time then I can now take; But this I am ſure of, that (whatſever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us) his Church wil be yet glorious in the <hi>World,</hi> and if we ſhould be ſcattered, there ſhall not a <hi>graine</hi> of the good corn be loſt; nay, that <hi>ſcattering</hi> (as the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſion of the Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.1, 4.) would but be a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29487:21"/>
                  <hi>ſeed</hi>-time, which would undoubtedly make way for <hi>a larger</hi> harveſt in other Kingdomes and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> 2. Let us not <hi>intercept</hi> the praiſe that is due to Chriſt, ſeeing the work is his, let him have the Honour of it; it is not for us to be ſolicitous about the advancement of our <hi>own</hi> glory: it is the Fathers deſigne that Chriſt ſhould <hi>in every</hi> thing have the <hi>preheminence;</hi> and if we could but ſo maſter the <hi>pride</hi> of our own hearts, as to be <hi>ſincerely nothing</hi> in our own eyes; even then when God doth <hi>moſt</hi> by us:<note place="margin">Prov. 10.7.</note> he that gives <hi>grace to the humble,</hi> will not be <hi>behind</hi> with us, he will look to our <hi>names</hi> to keep them from <hi>rotting;</hi> let him have his <hi>own</hi> in the <hi>firſt</hi> place, when he uſeth you as inſtruments in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and then ſee if he will <hi>grudge</hi> to <hi>perfume</hi> your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories in the Churches of God; though there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing due to the beſt of men, when they have done their utmoſt for him: yet, he doth vouchſafe to make them <hi>Co-partners</hi> in his praiſe, calling them <hi>Saviours,</hi> and <hi>repairers</hi> of the breach; let us be ſingle hearted, not minding our <hi>own</hi> things, nor ſtudying <hi>ſelfe-exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> 1. This is <hi>envious</hi> carriage toward Chriſt; <hi>a proud ſelf-ſeeking heart hath alwayes an evill eye,</hi> 2. Tis <hi>a vain</hi> attempt; Chriſt will have the honour whether you will or no, as he is the <hi>Alpha</hi> the beginner, and author of every work, ſo will he be the <hi>Omega,</hi> to whom all ſhall be aſcribed; tis as impoſſible for men to <hi>diveſt</hi> Chriſt of his Glory, as it is for them to <hi>muffle</hi> the Sun in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perpetuall darkneſſe, or, to <hi>impriſon</hi> the Rivers upon the earth; which, (though they may be diverted from their uſuall courſe, or dammed up for a ſpace) yet with <hi>a greater</hi> violence will break into the <hi>Ocean</hi> at laſt; 3. He that is <hi>ſecretly jealous</hi> that his glory will be ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed by giving all to Chriſt, ſhall certainly looſe the Honour he ſeeks after. 4. There is no ſuch <hi>lovely</hi> frame of ſpirit as that which makes a man willing to <hi>decreaſe,</hi> ſo that Chriſt may <hi>increaſe.</hi> Joh. 3.30.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:29487:21"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Mourne</hi> over the Temples <hi>deſolations;</hi> the building is glorious, and who can behold the ruines of it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out teares and ſadneſs? one can ſcarce be <hi>exceſſive</hi> in ſorrow for the calamities of the Church, except his griefe be mixed with <hi>repinings</hi> and <hi>diſtruſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Look abroad into the World, and conſider the face of things; you have heard what hath been done in <hi>Germany,</hi> and in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and of late in <hi>Piedmont</hi> and <hi>Poland;</hi> the horrid inquiſitions, <hi>bloody</hi> maſſacres, <hi>unmercifull</hi> expulſions, baniſhments and cruelties that the Church hath groaned under, you cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of; neither can we ſo eaſily forget what hath been done <hi>here</hi> in theſe Nations where we live: farre be it from me to <hi>nouriſh</hi> unthankfull <hi>murmurings</hi> againſt the goodneſſe of God, who hath given us ſo much <hi>liberty</hi> in the enjoyment of his Goſpell. Though we have <hi>great</hi> cauſe to be <hi>thankfull;</hi> yet, ſtill we have <hi>cauſe</hi> to take up a <hi>Lamentation,</hi> that the Sanctuary is not cleanſed, and that the building is not yet perfected; how fearfully are many <hi>drunk</hi> and <hi>mad</hi> with error? did thoſe honeſt hearts that ſo <hi>earneſtly</hi> followed God with tears when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation firſt was ſpoken of, ever <hi>think</hi> to hear ſo many outragious <hi>blaſphemies</hi> vented and pleaded for as now they do? how have we been <hi>undone</hi> by an <hi>unlimited Chriſtian-Liberty?</hi> who would have thought that this would have been wreſted to patronize <hi>licentiouſneſs?</hi> how <hi>unwilling</hi> are moſt to beare the <hi>yoke</hi> of Chriſts Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? how hath the Devill by <hi>little</hi> and <hi>little</hi> drawn men to a <hi>careleſſeneſſe</hi> of Religion, thereby making way to a <hi>growing Athieſme,</hi> as appears by the ſcorns of ſome, and the Apoſtaſies of others? how <hi>cowardly,</hi> and <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſhamefac'd</hi> are many, when they ſhould <hi>plead</hi> for God, and truth, as if their own hearts did <hi>ſecretly que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> the reality of Religion? how <hi>ſtrangely</hi> do many of the <hi>Gentry</hi> ſpend their time? what irreligious <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erleſſe</hi> families do ſome of them keep (when they ſhould ſhew better example to the meaner ſort (and yet,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29487:22"/>how conſid ently can they <hi>cenſure</hi> others for <hi>hypocrites,</hi> (ſometime <hi>unjuſtly</hi> concluding againſt the <hi>ſtrictneſſe</hi> of Gods wayes, from the <hi>hypocriſy</hi> of ſome Profeſſors,) not <hi>conſidering</hi> what their own carriage and vanity do <hi>teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie</hi> againſt themſelves? how do we needleſly <hi>multiply</hi> our controverſies and diſputes? and with what <hi>bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> do we manage them, even then when the ſtrife is meerly about <hi>words</hi> and <hi>method?</hi> and generally how is the Name of God and religion abuſed to <hi>ſerve</hi> the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns</hi> of men? what ſtrange <hi>Religious People</hi> have we? ſome muſt needs be religious by taking up a ſingular <hi>conceit</hi> and <hi>opinion,</hi> though a man may eaſily ſee their <hi>hearts</hi> through their <hi>lives:</hi> others have all their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on their <hi>tongues end;</hi> they can have <hi>good</hi> diſcourſes, and yet be <hi>unconſcionable</hi> in their callings, ſhops and tradings.</p>
               <p>Are not theſe <hi>inſtances</hi> enough to move your compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions? and yet I have not ſpoken all, neither can I. They have hard hearts that are not affected with theſe things; <hi>How is our ſilver become droſs, our wine mixed with water?</hi> upon the fall of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan, David</hi> taught the children of Iſrael the <hi>Bow;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.18. Weems Jud. Law. vol. 2. cap. 44.</note> not the art and uſe of ſhooting (as ſome expound) for they knew that before, but the <hi>Lamentation</hi> which was called the <hi>Bow,</hi> (it was uſuall to ſtile their Elegies and Songs by the names of <hi>Arcus, Ala, Securis, Scutum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Bow, wing,</hi> &amp;c.) much more reaſon have we to teach our hearts to mourn when the Sanctuary of the Lord lieth deſolate.</p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Pſ. 48.2.</note> The Church is a <hi>Glorious building,</hi> beautifull <hi>for ſituation, the Joy of</hi> the <hi>whole</hi> earth, and can thy heart be ſtrong, or, thine eyes forbear when thou beholdeſt <hi>this</hi> forſaken and made an <hi>heap? walk about Sion,</hi> tell the <hi>towers thereof,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 48.12.</note> 
                  <hi>mark well</hi> her bulwarks, it may be thou haſt not <hi>well conſidered</hi> her beauty, if thou haſt, thou canſt not but be diſtreſſed for it, when it becomes <hi>ſolitary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lam. 1.1. Eſa. 1.8.</note> and as a <hi>widow;</hi> when tis brought to this, to be like a <hi>cottage in a Vineyard, or a lodge in a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29487:22"/>garden of Cucumbers;</hi> can <hi>Jonah</hi> vex himſelf when his gourd withers? Can the Merchants of <hi>Tyre</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail the fall of their City? and ſhall not thy <hi>Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance be ſad</hi> (with <hi>Nehemiah</hi> chap. 2.3.) <hi>when the City, the place of thy fathers ſepulchers, lieth waſt, and the gates thereof are conſumed with fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. When it comes to this, then be ſure that God is very <hi>angry;</hi> he would not give his <hi>darling</hi> to <hi>the power of the</hi> dog upon a <hi>light</hi> diſpleaſure; and if the <hi>Lion roar, ſhall not all the beaſts of the forreſt tremble?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos 3.8.</note> Will not a towardly child be <hi>more</hi> troubled at the <hi>anger</hi> of his father, then at the <hi>ſmart</hi> of his <hi>rod?</hi> Have you found his loving kindneſs <hi>ſweet,</hi> his ſmiles <hi>better then life?</hi> and will not his <hi>frowns</hi> then <hi>cut</hi> you to the heart?</p>
               <p n="3">3. His people alſo are ſurely <hi>guilty</hi> of more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>ſins</hi> at ſuch a time; if any ask, Why hath the <hi>Lord done thus</hi> to his people?<note place="margin">Deut. 29.24.</note> What <hi>meaneth the heat of his great anger?</hi> Will not any one return this anſwer; They have <hi>ſinned greatly,</hi> God doth not uſe ſeverity but upon great provocations, and doth not ſin call for mourning?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Gods honour ſeems to <hi>ſuffer</hi> deeply, when the Church is troden down and laid waſt, and is this <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> to you?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Gods <hi>Children</hi> have uſually been <hi>overwhelmed</hi> with grief upon this occaſion. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> deſires to weep a flood of tears for this, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.1. <hi>Oh! that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountain of tears that I might weep day and night,</hi> &amp;c. And yet he wept till ſorrow over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him, till his heart was ready to break, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.19. <hi>My bowels, my bowels, I am pained at the very heart, my heart maketh a noiſe in me, I cannot hold my peace, becauſe thou haſt heard, O my Soul, the ſound of the trumpet,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Eſay</hi> is <hi>reſolute</hi> in Lamentation and (like <hi>Rachel</hi> weeping for her children) will not be comforted, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 22.4. <hi>Look away from me, I will weep bitterly, labour not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me; becauſe of the ſpoiling of the daughter of my
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29487:23"/>people.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eze. 9.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Ezra pluckt</hi> off the <hi>hair of his head and the hair of his beard, and ſits down aſtonied. Daniel</hi> refuſeth his comforts and refreſhments;<note place="margin">Dan. 10.2.</note> 
                  <hi>He eat not pleaſant bread, neither came fleſh nor wine in his mouth, neither did be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint himſelf till three weeks were fulfilled.</hi> If thy heart then be not Adamant or Steel, thou canſt not chuſe but weep for company.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If thou canſt not mourn for the Church, thou wilt at leaſt have cauſe to mourn <hi>for thy ſelf,</hi> both for thy <hi>obdurateneſs</hi> and for the <hi>judgements</hi> thou ſhalt ſurely feel; if God ſhould <hi>ſweep</hi> us away in a common <hi>deluge,</hi> yet, he will <hi>provide</hi> an <hi>Ark</hi> for the mourners of Sion. He would be a <hi>little ſanctuary to them in the Countries where they ſhould come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 11.16.</note> and for that end he ſets a <hi>mark</hi> upon ſuch;<note place="margin">Ezek. 9.4, 6.</note> but for ſuch as are <hi>at-eaſe</hi> not <hi>grieving for the afflictions of Joſeph,</hi> they ſhall have the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt</hi> ſhare of the Judgements, <hi>Amos</hi> 6.1, 4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>They are not grieved for the affliction of Joſeph, Therefore, now ſhall they go captive with the firſt that go captive,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It may be, when you hear the <hi>words</hi> of this <hi>curſe,</hi> you <hi>bleſs</hi> your ſelves in your <hi>heart,</hi> ſuppoſing that you have learned and practiſed this leſſon; let me therefore bring your grief to the <hi>touch-ſtone,</hi> by propounding two or three Queſtions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What is it that <hi>moſt afflicts thee?</hi> Is it the <hi>loſſe</hi> of thine eſtate or friends? Is it the <hi>advancement</hi> of ſome <hi>meaner</hi> perſons to riches and command: whilſt thou fitteſt at their <hi>foot-ſtool?</hi> Is it becauſe thy <hi>way</hi> or <hi>party</hi> doth not <hi>thrive</hi> as thou wouldeſt have it? If theſe <hi>only</hi> grieve thee, then it is thy <hi>pride, wordlineſs, envy,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſelfiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> that troubles thee; but how doth the <hi>ſpiritual deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> the <hi>unprofitableneſs</hi> and <hi>unfruitfulneſs</hi> of the Church affect thee? Are thoſe a ſword in thy bones?</p>
               <p n="2">2. What doſt thou <hi>moſt deſire</hi> for the Church? What wouldſt thou have (if thou mighteſt) at the <hi>firſt wiſh?</hi> Ask thy heart? Wouldſt thou have <hi>God recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled</hi> to us? Wouldſt thou have the <hi>light</hi> of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance?</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:29487:23"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>How much</hi> art thou troubled? How <hi>deep</hi> goes thy grief? Coulſt thou be pleaſed to have thy <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>plenty,</hi> to enjoy thy <hi>deſires</hi> in a <hi>corner,</hi> and let become of the Church <hi>what will?</hi> Is thy bed <hi>eaſy,</hi> thy ſleep <hi>ſweet,</hi> thy eſtate <hi>comfortable,</hi> whilſt the Name of God is <hi>prophaned</hi> and <hi>blaſphemed?</hi> Or rather, is not all <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> to thee whilſt it is <hi>thus?</hi> Or, canſt thou <hi>ſolidly</hi> and <hi>ſeriouſly</hi> mourn more for the <hi>Churches</hi> miſeries then for thy <hi>perſonal</hi> afflictions? Canſt thou lament at the <hi>rate</hi> of <hi>Eli</hi> and his <hi>daughter</hi>-in-law, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.22. Is it the <hi>Chief</hi> of thy ſorrow that the <hi>Ark</hi> of God is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken?</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>What</hi> wouldſt thou be <hi>content</hi> to <hi>do</hi> for the help of the Church? Couldſt thou give thy <hi>pleaſant</hi> things for it? How <hi>oft,</hi> or how <hi>earneſtly</hi> doſt thou <hi>wraſtle</hi> with God on her behalf? What <hi>ſins</hi> (for they are the troubles of Iſrael) haſt thou <hi>left</hi> for her ſake? Couldſt thou be content to <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> thy <hi>honour,</hi> and <hi>eſtate</hi> for it? What haſt thou <hi>done</hi> to heal it? Haſt thou <hi>proſecuted</hi> her peace? Art thou willing, for thy part, to lay down thy own <hi>conceits</hi> and <hi>opinions,</hi> to abate ſomething of thy <hi>ſtifneſs,</hi> rather then ſhe ſhould be <hi>undone</hi> by continual diviſions? They are <hi>idle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> non vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit ſe deleri è libro vitae <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino;</hi> Sed <hi>Phyſico.</hi> Vult Apostolus perire in carne, ut alii ſalvean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in ſpiritu.</note> 
                  <hi>unprofitable and unacceptable tears that are not joined with endeavours. Moſes</hi> could be content to be <hi>blotted out of Gods book,</hi> rather then the Church ſhould be laid waſte, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.32. <hi>Paul</hi> would be <hi>an Anathema for Iſraels ſake,</hi> Rom. 9.3. (not that theſe deſires <hi>reached</hi> ſo far as <hi>eternal</hi> death: but, that they were willing to ſuffer a <hi>temporal</hi> death; or, thoſe <hi>tortures</hi> which ſometime ſeiſed upon the bodies of thoſe who were <hi>delivered</hi> to Sathan by <hi>excommunication</hi>) they were willing to <hi>buy</hi> the Churches peace with <hi>death</hi> and <hi>ſufferings,</hi> and wilt thou do nothing for it?<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Arrow-Smith,</hi> Tract. ſacr. lib <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> Sect. X, XI.</note> be not <hi>deceived,</hi> God will not be <hi>mocked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> 4. Chriſt will build his Temple. Therefore <hi>let us be ſtrong, riſe up</hi> and <hi>build,</hi> work, for He alſo will work; do not think (you that are <hi>private</hi> Chriſtians) that you are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29487:24"/>
                  <hi>unconcerned</hi> in this duty, the meaneſt of you may do <hi>ſomething,</hi> they that have no <hi>gold</hi> may yet bring <hi>badgers</hi> skins,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.12.</note> or <hi>goats</hi> hair for the ſanctuary: If <hi>there be a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling mind it is accepted according to what a man hath.</hi> Magiſtrates and Miniſters are ſpecially to look to this, I ſhall therefore ſpeak to you both in a few directions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Be <hi>like minded,</hi> be of <hi>one accord;</hi> it is the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles direction, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.2. If the builders <hi>diſagree</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves the work will <hi>ceaſe,</hi> if the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found your <hi>Languages,</hi> it will be but a <hi>Babel.</hi> But you will ſay, you have not ſo much power over your <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> as to believe <hi>any thing;</hi> you hold nothing but what you <hi>take</hi> to be <hi>truth.</hi> Anſw. 1. Though your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions do <hi>differ,</hi> yet you may all have the <hi>ſame deſign</hi> of peace. 2. You may all <hi>ſpeak the ſame things,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.10. You <hi>agree</hi> in the <hi>main,</hi> and you need not <hi>ſpeak</hi> or <hi>urge</hi> thoſe things wherein you think <hi>differently:</hi> you ought not to <hi>dote about Queſtions which gender ſtrife.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Condeſcend</hi> one to another as much as may be, it is in <hi>vain</hi> to expect concord <hi>without</hi> this; the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.12. enjoins the ſtrong to <hi>bear the infirmities of the weak,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Vid. Willet in loc. &amp; Leigh. Crit. ſac.</note> not onely to <hi>tollerate</hi> them, but to take them <hi>upon our ſelves,</hi> to <hi>trouble</hi> our ſelves with them, by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking to <hi>cure</hi> them, <hi>in nos ſuſcipere ut curemus;</hi> and for this end, commands that we ſtudy to <hi>pleaſe our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for his good,</hi> rather then <hi>our ſelves;</hi> that is, in <hi>ſmall</hi> matters, not to uſe the <hi>utmoſt</hi> of our own <hi>liberty</hi> and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, but to <hi>ſuffer</hi> ſome <hi>inconveniences</hi> that way, by <hi>condeſcention.</hi> We are engaged to this, by the <hi>rule of expediency,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.12.</note> (all <hi>things are lawful, but all are not expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient</hi>) by <hi>the law of Charity</hi> (Rom. 14.15. thou walkeſt <hi>not charitably, thou deſtroyeſt thy brother by the liberty</hi>) and <hi>by our own need (lege talionis)</hi> the <hi>beſt</hi> of us ſhall ſtand in need of the condeſcention of <hi>other men</hi> to us, as well as they may need <hi>ours</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> the <hi>head cannot ſay to the foot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>I have no need of thee,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.21. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould have the <hi>ſame care one to another,</hi> v. 25.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29487:24"/>ſtudying how to <hi>accommodate</hi> our ſelves to <hi>others</hi> as well as how <hi>others</hi> may yied <hi>to us.</hi> He that will not <hi>learn</hi> this <hi>leſſon,</hi> ſhall <hi>never</hi> be honoured with the titles of <hi>healer</hi> and <hi>peace-maker.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Let nothing be done <hi>Through ſtrife or vain glory,</hi> Phil. 2.3. though you do not <hi>croſs</hi> one another, yet if you are carried up by <hi>theſe principles,</hi> you will <hi>one time or other fail, grow pettiſh, and undo all again,</hi> as your temptations lead you; nay, God may <hi>refuſe</hi> to accept, or bleſs your endeavours. Such a <hi>perverſe,</hi> croſs <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> may expect to be thrown <hi>up again</hi> by the fire of divine <hi>jealouſy,</hi> as that of the Temple was in the times of <hi>Julian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Let the work be <hi>ſuitable to the foundation;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.12.</note> build not <hi>hay and ſtubble</hi> upon it, <hi>trifle</hi> not in a work ſo <hi>weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>ſerious,</hi> regard that <hi>moſt</hi> which is not <hi>neceſſary,</hi> buſy not your ſelves ſo much about <hi>petty ornaments</hi> for the houſe, till the <hi>main</hi> work (foundation, walls, and roof) <hi>be up.</hi> How <hi>much</hi> of Religion and Reformation is placed in <hi>Circumſtances</hi> (by ſome) in a <hi>Garbe, forme</hi> and a <hi>nicety</hi> of <hi>affected</hi> expreſſions; I am aſhamed to think how ſome <hi>diſgrace</hi> Religion this way, <hi>Tything Mint, Annis, and Cummin, while the weightier matters of the Law are neglected.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. If you are not <hi>perfectly joined together in the ſame mind and judgment</hi> about ſome diſputable things, yet <hi>cenſure not</hi> one another for differences. All of you may <hi>hold the head,</hi> though your conſciences <hi>be not alike ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> in all things; nay, be not <hi>over</hi> confident of your own underſtandings: (I am ſpeaking of the diſputes about Diſcipline and Government) ſome of you (it may be) <hi>have</hi> been confident heretofore of ſomething which now you <hi>judge</hi> an <hi>errour,</hi> and why may you not ſuppoſe that your <hi>preſent</hi> confidence may poſſibly <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> you, in what you <hi>now take</hi> to be truth; be <hi>modeſt</hi> and <hi>jealous</hi> of your ſelves, have <hi>Charity</hi> for thoſe that think not as you do; it is a <hi>Common fault</hi> among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29487:25"/>the <hi>reſpect and love they carry to a perſon, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> their affections and judgements to his way and opinion;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yet <hi>they venture</hi> boldly to condemn others for what t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> underſtand not.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Be <hi>laborious</hi> in your <hi>ſtations;</hi> there goes m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>more</hi> to building then bare <hi>wiſhes;</hi> though it will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be effected by humane <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>might</hi> alone; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it will never be done <hi>without means,</hi> men think t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> have done <hi>all</hi> when they <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> a paper, or <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> conſent to ſuch a way, and then blame others beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the work is not done. What? Do you think the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming of a model for Government and the Recomm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, or Eſtabliſhment of it is <hi>all</hi> that is required <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Compleating of the Lords Houſe? If the Supre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſhould interpoſe his authority, and bring on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> work thus <hi>far,</hi> yet ſtill the <hi>fitting</hi> and <hi>ſquaring</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> materials would be a ſufficient task both for Miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and others; do not think to <hi>reap</hi> without <hi>plowing</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſowing:</hi> ſet to it then with all your might, and, quicken you, let me recommend to you the dilig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> peruſal of Mr. <hi>Baxters book of the Reformed Paſtor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Join prudence</hi> to <hi>zeal,</hi> this is neceſſary; it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> enough to be a <hi>forward</hi> actor, except you have <hi>skill</hi> take the advantages and fitteſt opportunities; the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of man worketh not the righteouſneſs of God, <hi>Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 20. How <hi>unſerviceable</hi> do many Good Chriſtians ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>themſelves</hi> by <hi>imprudence?</hi> This occaſions <hi>miſtakes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>offences,</hi> brings <hi>grace</hi> under <hi>ſuſpicion</hi> of hypocriſy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at leaſt, <hi>blocks</hi> up the way by <hi>prejudice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Build in <hi>Gods way;</hi> expect not to ſee the happin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Church by <hi>man-pleaſing</hi> or <hi>flattery;</hi> this Fabri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> will not ſtand if it be <hi>daubed</hi> with <hi>untempered mort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Be <hi>faithful</hi> to the Souls of men, though in ſo doing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>diſpleaſe</hi> them, ſtill aim at holineſs, be alwaies <hi>preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> forward,</hi> towards perfection; So ſhall the counſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of Peace at laſt be eſtabliſhed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
